In this class. We are going to discuss about
CMOS Nor gate in the last class. We designed
nand gate by using CMOS
So as you know that CMOS having two mos transistors
that is P mos and N mos It's just having P
mos as pull up and N mos as you pull down and
here when we are designing any gate or any
functionality. Then you need to give P mos
functionality of that particular functionality.
As pull up and the N Mo's logic of that particular
functionality as pull down here. We are going
to design CMOS nor gate if you want CMOS nor
gate you need to Cascade P mos nor gate as
pull-up and n mos nor gate as pull down here.You
can absorb up to here. This is p mos nor gate
and this is n mos nor gate by connecting this
P mos and N mos nor gate you are going to
get Get your CMOS nor gate this P mos nor gate
and CMOS nor gate we already discussed
in the last two classes. Now, we will see
this circuit will work for nor operation or
not that will see now. So here we are having
two inputs A and B same inputs. We are giving
for both p mos and n mos so here. I am considering
that inputs a b and I am just considering
my P Mo's transistor cells q1 and Q2 and then
n  mos transistors as Q3 and Q4. So here Q1
Q2 Q3 Q4 and your output Vo so now for
two input variables you are combinations maybe
four that four combinations are 0 0 0 1 1 0
1 1 now as you know that P mos will on
this is p, Mos So P mos will on for 0 and
off for 1This is n mos.So n mos will on for
1 and off for 0. So now when you are output
is going to get 0 when you are output is going
to get one means whenever you are output is
connected to Vdd. Then you are coming in getting
high voltage at output when you were output
is connected to ground by this way or this
way, then you are going to get zero at output.
So when you are going to connect to ground
means whenever anyone of this n Mo's transistor
is on then it will forms shorts circuit. by
that short circuit path you are going to connect
with the ground then coming to hear when your output is going to connect with Vdd means
Whenever two transistors whenever both transistors
P Mo's transistors are on then only you are
output is going to connect with vdd or otherwise
if anyone of the one transistor P Mo's transistor
is off then the short circuit path will cut
then you are Output is not going to connect
with your supply voltage. So in that case
it's going to connect with ground. So now
see the operation here. So whenever both transistors
are on then only it's going to connect with
VDD.
So if anyone of this transistor is on then
it's going to connect with ground. So now
see here when we given 0 0 So these two are
P Mo's transistors and these two are n Mo's
transistors. So when we give input as 0 P
Mo's transistors are going to on and n mos
is going to off.So see here. So n mos is going
to off here You'll get open circuit.
So here you will get open circuit. So like
this you will get opens circuit and here both
transistors Both p mos are on means here like
this You are having short circuit. So now
you can imagine so this Vo is not having
path like this this this same Vo is not
having any path like this because here It's
having actually two paths like this or like
this the two parts are in opens  circuited
So that means we are not having any connection
in between Vo and ground and now you can see
you are having this short circuit path from
Vo to VDD in this case you are output is equal
to one or high voltage vdd now in case
of 0 1 if you give A equal to 0 B equal to
1 then p mos will on for zero n mos will off for
zero that means for same for P Mo's transistor
will on but this n Mo's transistor will off
so here. So for one, your p mos will
off and n mos will on n mos will on so you
can see here.
So this whatever q1 is there that is on that
means up to here you. Having short circuit
but coming to Q2. This is open circuited because
Q2 is off. That means open circuited then
coming to this connection. So Q3 is off Q3
is open circuited, but Q4 is on Q4 is on means
like this. So now you can observe really clear
any path that here to here here you have open
path. That means the Vo to VDD connection
is lost here due to this open circuit and
you are having a short path between Vo to ground
by this Q4. So now in this case you are output
is going to connect with ground through this
short circuit path forward by Q4 N mos transistor.
Then in this case you are output is equal
to 0 now. come to 1 0 combination. If you give
an A is equal to 1 B is equal to 0 if you
given a equal one P mos is going to
off. And your n mos is going to on. So if
you give any A as 1 p mos is going to off
n mos is going to on the same way If you give
B is equal to 0 you are P mos is going
to on your P mos is going to on and your n
mos is going to off now. I can see the connection.
So if Q1 is off you are having open circuit
here and when Q2 is on you are having short
circuit like this and when Q3 Is on you are
having short circuit like this and Q4 is off
Mean. Now This is open circuited. Now, you
can see where you are having path Vo to VDD
path is lost because of this opens circuit so
up to here you are having bar, but here this
is open circuited and coming to here here.
This is open circuited. But here you are having
path to ground. So you are having in this
case you are having  Vo to ground connection
through this Q3 short circuit path. In this
case. Also, your output is going to connect
with ground means you are getting zero.So
now in case of 1 1, if you are providing
a equal to 1 b equal to 1 you are both p mo's
are transistors are going to off that means
so like this and both n mos on like this so
here both are of means both Having opens circuit
and here both are having short circuit in
this case. Also your now you lost path between
Vo to V DD because of this open circuit and
here by this way or this way your output
is going to connect with ground. So that means
you're going to get zero and it is connected
with ground. It's going to get 0 now. You
can observe this truth table. If You observe
this truth table whenever all All signals
are all inputs are 0 then only or getting
one if any one of the input is 1 then you
are getting 0 at output. So this is the meaning
of nor operation. So by this functionality
functional truth table obtained by the circuit
so we can say this circuit will act as nor
gate so as this is CMOS logic, so this this
is called as CMOS nor gate.