In this class We are going to discuss about
CMOS nand gate in the last class. We discussed
the about designing of same nand gate by using
P mos and n mos in this class we going to discuss designing nand gate by using CMOS logic.
So as you know, that CMOS is the combination
of P mos and n mos as P mos is taken as pull-up
transistor and then n mos is taken under pulled down. So here same For Designing CMOS nand
gate also P mos nand is considered upside.
So n mos and is considered as pulled off So
here you can absorb.This is p mo's nand gate
and this is again n mos nand gate both are cascaded
in vertical like this.Then it will form CMOS
nand gate now. We will see it will works as
a CMOS nand or not. So here for the time considering
say A B values here.A B and you are transistors.
So that means Q1 Q2 Q3 Q4 and your output
voltage Vo. So see when your output
Vo is equal and to 1 means whenever it is
connected to Vdd by anyway, then only your output
connected to ground whenever it's connecting
to ground even though it is connected to Vdd
see here don't confuse for P mos N mos and
all this so here whenever you take an output
in middle, so whenever it is connected to
ground, so even though it is connected for Vdd
we will assume 0 so now see here
so the combinations are 0 0 0 1 1 0 and 1
1 that means you know that for P mos So this
is p mos is only on for zero and off for
one like that N mos will on for one and off
for zero. So, you know that Q3 and Q4 are
n mos and q1 and Q2 are P mos these two are
P Mo's transistors and these two are n mos
transistors. So this is n mos so now I'm just
writing switch off on  values of
this transistors for n mos and p mos so whenever
a equal to 0 b equal to 0 whenever a equal
to 0 B equal to 0 both p mo's are going
to on that means so Q1 on Q2 on same low voltage
if we're given two n mos then those are going
to off So any mosfet is off means it will
be open circuited here. These two transistors
are off mean is here you are getting open
circuit path? And here these two p mo's are on means here. You are having short path like
this or like this then in this case you are
output is going to cut with this ground. And
this is going to connect with your Source
voltage in this case You are getting one Output.
So now in this case second case zero one condition.
So in zero one condition your Q1 is going
to on and you are Q2 is going to off as that
is p mos for p mos . If you given high voltage
and that's going to off reverse case in n
mos if you given high voltage then Q4 is going
to on and here here A is 0 then this n mos
is going to Off so here n mos is going to
off for 0 and N mos is going to on for one.Now.
You can see the connection q1 is on you are
having short path like this Q 1 is on and you
are you Q2 is off that means here you are
having open circuit and here you can absorb
your Q3 is off that means here. You are having
open path by It's open path you are output
is going to cut with this ground. Even though
you are Q4 is short circuited as Q3 is
open circuited your path is going to cut with
output. Then this output is going to connect
with Vdd through Q1 see Q1 is on means you
are having short circuit So now this output
is going to connect through Q1 to Vdd. So
anyway, it's connected to Vdd means you are
getting high output. So in next case 1 0 case
in this case you are first two p mos is going
to off and the second p mos is going to on
because we provided zero reverse of that if
you provided one here Q3 is on and as you
provided 0 here Q4 is off that means n
mos will off for low voltage So you will see
so here your second transistor is on. That
means here you are having short path and here
coming to here. So this is on and this is
off. That means Q3 is on but Q4 is off from
output to here. You are having short path.
When coming to here you are having open path
by this opens circuit Our your connection is going
to lose from Vo to ground. Then this Vo is
going to connect with this VDD through this
Q2 p mos.
So then when it Is connected to Vdd here itself
here. Also, you are going to get one at output
are high voltage at the output in case of
1 1 that means both p mo's and n mos are given
with one in both input case that means so
A is equal to 1 B is equal to 1 so far this
both p mos are going to off both n mos are
going to on both p mos are going to off
means you are going to lose your Connection
from output to Source voltage and both n mos
is going to on means you are going to get
shotrs circuit path from output to ground.These
two n mos are going to on means here. You
are having short path from output to ground
and you are losing this connection because
of open path in Q1 and Q2. Both p mo's are
off means both having open circuit. There
is no way to connect with VDD So in this case,
As output is connecting with to ground you
are going to get 0 volts at output If You
observe this truth table when you are providing
at least one low input, then you are getting
high output whenever all the inputs are high
then only you are going to get low voltage
at output. That means this is the nand functionality.
This is Nand functionality. That means 1 into
0 whole bar 1 0 into one whole bar Do I need
to 0 whole bar 1 1 into one whole bar 0 so
we can set that by observing. This truth table
came from the circuit so we can say that this
will works as nand gate So this is the designing
of CMOS nand gate. So CMOS is nothing
but integrating P Mos with n mos p mos structure
as pull up and n mos structure as pull down.
So like this way we can design any circuit
in CMOS functionality by using CMOS logic