a gated set/reset latch is an SR latch
that can only change state while it's
enabled for example imagine an air
conditioning system in a building each
room could have its own cooling unit
controlled independently by its own SR
latch the set and reset signals might
come from a temperature sensor or a
humidity sensor in the room if these
were gated SR latches then a central
control panel could be used to enable or
disable the switching on and off of
these units on a room-by-room basis
here's an Un-gated SR latch remember an
SR latch built from nor gates like this
one is an active high SR latch this
means it requires a high pulse that's a
1 to be applied at input s in order to
get a high output at Q in other words to
set the latch alternatively to reset the
latch and make the output at Q zero it
requires a high pulse to be applied to
input arm it's invalid for both s and R
to be made high at the same time an SR
latch is said to be level sensitive this
means it will respond to a valid change
in either S or R regardless of the
duration of the input pulse it's the
level high or low that matters not how
long it's applied for to build a gated
SR latch we can make some simple
enhancements to an SR latch by
connecting a pair of and gates in series
with the inputs of an or based SR latch
we've created a third input E which can
be used to enable or disable the
latching effect a regular and gate will
only have a high output if both inputs
are high so only when E is set to one
with a one from s or a one from r get
through to our cross connected nor gates
here's an SR latch built from NAND gates
this is a level sensitive
active low sr latch in other words both
s and r are normally high and it
requires a low pulse that's a zero to be
applied to s in order to set it it also
requires a low pulse to be applied to R
in order to reset it by connecting an
extra pair of NAND gates to the latch
like this not only have we created a
third input E we now have a new circuit
in which the normal states of s and r
are zero and high pulses are required to
set or reset the latch in other words
our NAND based latch has been changed
from an active low latch into an active
high latch these additional gates on a
basic SR latch are sometimes referred to
as steering gates an SR latch without
steering gates is said to be transparent
a valid input will affect the output
unconditionally a gated SR latch on the
other hand is transparent only when it's
enabled it's convenient to give a gated
SR latch its own symbol because we can
now focus on what the latch does rather
than what's going on inside it the
inputs S E and R are still shown and so
is the output q and its inverse not Q
we can illustrate what's going on at any
one of the inputs or the output on a
chart showing changes in voltage against
time at any given moment the voltage
will be either low zero volts to all
intents and purposes and representing
the binary value zero or high at about
five volts representing the binary value
one now of course everything can happen
very quickly in a digital circuit each
time interval on this chart could be in
the order of a microsecond that's a
millionth of a second
having said that for a level sensitive
gated SR latch each time interval might
be one second or one minute or even an
hour it really depends on the
application for the purposes of this
discussion it takes no time for the
voltage to change from low to high or
from high to low in reality this
transition takes a few nanoseconds the
significance of which we'll ignore for
now but come back to in a later video
let's proceed on the assumption that
switching from low to high or vice-versa
is instantaneous this gives us the
classic square wave that you can see
here we now have a convenient way to
describe the behavior of a latch by
stacking several charts together one for
each input S R D and one for the output Q
with a common time axis we can visualize
this circuit in action at the time
indicated by the vertical yellow line
the output Q is low s and R are also
both low but E is high so the latch is
enabled in fact in this diagram the
latch is always enabled so it's going to
behave exactly like a simple SR latch
without steering gates as time passes if
s goes high
so does Q because it's a latch when s
drops to low again Q stays high
if s goes high while Q is high it has no
effect Q is already high when R goes
high Q goes low when s goes high again
so does Q this is normal latching
behavior
again we see R going high so the
latches reset again the latch is already
reset so another pulse at R has no
effect now let's examine what happens
when E varies you can see that some of
the time he is high and some of the time
E is low we begin with an output of
zero at Q and because E is low the
latch is disabled s goes high but it has
no effect on the output of the latch now
E is high the latch is enabled so when
s goes high
so does Q and when s drops too low again
the latch stays high until such time as
R goes high and then Q drops to zero
again now E is zero the latch is no
longer enabled so if s goes high it has
no effect on Q
E is high again the latch is enabled
and so it responds when s goes high the
latch is set again E goes to zero the
latch is disabled R goes high but Q
doesn't drop it remains in its high
state to summarize that an SR latch
built from nor gates can be turned into
a gated SR latch by adding a pair of and
gates to it an SR latch built from NAND
gates can be turned into a gated SR
latch by adding another pair of NAND
gates to it this also has the effect of
changing the SR latch from an active low
to an active high latch a gated SR latch
has an additional input e which must be
high before the latch will respond to
any changes in S or R the gated SR latch
has its own symbol to simplify diagrams
and the behavior of a latch can be
described by means of a timing diagram