laches and flip-flops are the building
blocks of computer memory in this
particular video will focus on the
so-called SR latch later we'll see how
this circuit can be enhanced the
set/reset latch or SR latch for short
can be thought of as a 1-bit memory it
can be put into one of two stable output
States triggered by an input pulse the
circuit remembers this state until it's
changed again by another input pulse or
until the power is removed for this
reason the circuit is known as a
bi-stable latch before we consider the
construction of SR latches let's remind
ourselves of some fundamental logic
gates this is an or gate and this is the
truth table that describes its behavior
any combination of inputs A and B
results in a 1 an output P except when
both inputs are 0 in which case the
output is 0 this is an and gate and this
is the truth table that describes its
behavior any combination of inputs A and
B results in a 0 at output P except when
both inputs are 1 in which case the
output is 1 if we modify the output of a
regular or gate by inverting it with a
not gate then we can swap the 0 for a 1
and the ones for zeros in the output
column of the truth table
in a similar fashion we can invert the
output of a regular and gate then we can
swap the zeros for ones and the one for
a zero in the output column of this
truth table
each of these gate combinations has its
own name and its own symbol they are
known as the nor gate and the NAND gate
the nor gate only produces an output of
one if both of the inputs are zero the
NAND gate only produces an output of
zero if both of the inputs are one the
SR latch can be built using one of these
two basic building blocks let's start by
considering an SR latch built from nor
gates in this nor gate version of an SR
latch two nor gates are connected
together in such a way as the output of
each nor gate is one of the inputs of
the other this cross coupling of two
gates results in a form of positive
feedback SR latches like all electronic
circuits require power to work the power
connections aren't shown on this diagram
the SR latch has two inputs R and s and
the output Q the SR latch also makes the
inverse of the output available on this
diagram you can see not Q a Q
with a bar above it the starting state
here is that s and R are both low that
is both inputs are 0 Q is high that is
the output is one and not Q the inverse
of this is 0 both of the inputs of the
top nor gate are 0 so the output of the
top gate is 1 this is exactly what you
would expect from a nor gate the inputs
of the lower nor gate are 1 and 0 so the
output of the lower gate is 0 because Q
is 1 the latch is currently storing 1
now we apply a pulse to input R to reset
the latch this changes the output of the
top gate and then this is fed back into
the lower gate the lower gates output
also change
and this is fed back into the top gate
the pulse that was applied to reset the
SR latch is then removed and R is zero
again but the output at Q is now zero so
the latch is now storing a zero in order
to store a 1 again a pulse must be
applied to input s which will set the
latch again notice how the various
changes are propagated around the
circuit the set pulse is then removed
and the circuit is now latched into a
set state it's storing a 1 again notice
that if another set pulse is applied it
has no effect applying a set pulse at s
will always force the latch into a set
state regardless of the previous state
of the latch similarly applying a reset
pulse will always force the latch into a
reset state it should be noted that s
and R are never left high that is
neither is ever set continuously to the
value 1 the latch is controlled by
pulses only this gives us an
unusual-looking truth table when both s
and r are set to 0 q may be one or it
may be 0 depending on the previous state
of the circuit let's examine the truth
table as this SR latch is reset again
the reset pulse is applied s is 0 R is 1
output Q is 0 and it's inverse not Q
is 1 the SR latch is storing a 0 the
reset pulse is removed both s and r are
0 again output Q remains at 0 and it's
inverse remains at 1 the SR latch is
still storing a 0 a set pulse is applied
s is 1 and R is 0 the
output Q becomes one and its inverse
becomes zero the set pulse is removed s
is 0 and R is 0 output Q is still 1 and
not Q is of course 0 now the only
circumstance we haven't considered is
when both inputs s and R are set to 1 at
the same time if this were to occur
we'd be telling the SR latch to set the
value of Q to both 1 and 0
simultaneously in reality Q would become
0 and not Q would also become 0 this
would sort itself out if one of the
inputs fell to 0 before the other for
example if our fell to 0 first with s
still at 1 then Q would become 1 again
if however both inputs are at 1 and both
fell to 0 at the same time we have
what's known as a race condition between
the two gates
they'd be racing each other to feedback
their new output and it's impossible to
know which one would win hence if both
inputs are high the next state of the
latch can't be determined this is not a
state that the latch should ever be in
it's illegal it's invalid most of the
time inputs s and R should both be at 0
and only momentarily will one or the
other input become 1 and at any time
while it's operating the SR latch should
neither be in the set state or a reset
state with Q and not Q the opposite of
each other one final piece of
terminology this type of SR latch is
said to be an active high SR latch
because the normal condition for s and R
is low and a high pulse at one of these
inputs is required to bring about a
change now let's consider an SR latch
built from NAND gates here's a reminder
of the NAND gate truth table only when
both inputs are high is the output low
the wiring of this SR latch is the same
but notice that input s is at the top
now and R is at the bottom here's a
truth table for this variation of the SR
latch it's a little different from the
truth table we've just seen because this
latch behaves differently the difference
is that R and s are kept high most of
the time here we can see that output Q
is zero so the latch is storing a zero
when input s is made low momentarily
that is when s becomes zero and R is
still one the output at Q becomes one
the latch is now storing a one and s can
be returned to its normal high state
when R is set low momentarily the output
at Q is changed to 0 R can then return
to its normal high value and the latch
is now storing a zero again an SR latch
built from NAND gates like this is more
explicitly known as an active low sr
latch an SR latch based on NAND gates
also has a forbidden state that is when
both s and R are simultaneously 0 this
would result in an illegal state in
which both Q and its complement are 1 to
summarize them an SR latch can be built
from nor gates or from NAND gates both
types of latch do the same job but they
just controlled in a slightly different
way the nor gate based SR latch is set
or reset with high logic that is it is
an active high SR latch the NAND gate SR
latch on the other hand is set or reset
with low logic that is it's an active
low sr latch let's consider a particular
application of an SR latch when a
mechanical switch is pressed it may
actually generate several electrical
signals in a tiny fraction of a second
when only one signal is required
lots of on-off signals like this could
then cause problems with the circuit
that this switch is supposed to be
controlling the effect is known as
switch bands an integrated circuit with
an SR latch on it can be purchased
commercially to allow clean interfacing
between a mechanical switch and the
digital circuit it's controlling here we
can see a switch that will connect input
s which is currently high to earth
making it low and thereby changing the
output of this NAND based SR latch from
low to high this SR latch will ignore
any further set signals after it's
already been set so it's serving to
debounce
the signal from the mechanical switch
you can imagine other systems which
might make good use of this debouncing
effect for example a burglar alarm may
be triggered when a window or a door is
opened but we don't want the alarm bell
to stop ringing if the burglar shuts the
door on its own an SR latch has a few
uses mainly in control applications
where we need to monitor some condition
that might change or change back again
and react accordingly but more
importantly as you'll see later the
simple SR latch is the building block of
sophisticated memory circuits