Hello friends, Today topic is DRAM what is the full form of dynamic Random
Access Memory first you will see working of 1T.
That is one transistor DRAM  then we will see 3 Transistor DRAM. So let's start  so let's go for the first one
That is one transistor DRAM. so let's see this circuit first.
To draw this circuit. First we need the first word line.
Then we need the data line dot means connection is present here i have not draw any dots
so there is no connection.
so here we have connection that we are using access transistor so access transistor  is this let's say M .
Then we have one capacitor this will  store the charges right and then we will have one more
capacitor.
This is circuit of one transistor DRAM
You can see only one transistor. so what is the working let's see that the first point
what we have is  a read  operation in read operation, you have to understand this that we are making this capacitor equals to VDD by two.
so this is re charge to VDD by 2 and now why VDD by 2 ? it will be understood in futher steps so the second part is if word line is one
what will happen if this is one then this transistor will be on so M = on.
if this is on this capacitor can check its voltage with dataline if this is on
If the capacitor has voltage, it will be shared
if the voltage is 0 it will be shared to this line
now we have to understand that since VL is VDD by 2  so here we have VDD by 2
and second point is if Word line is one . this transistor is on
and we don't know whether the voltage here is 1/0 if it is one
if voltage is present higher then if Cs has
has the voltage of one then what will happen the voltage
would be shared here and collector voltage will be greater than VDD by two
if this is the voltage of Data line
and if it is send to sense amplifier
What will happen?
Yes the sense Amplifier will say that the output is 1 so this is the flow lets take a quick recap
first we have to make this capacitor as VDD by 2. Secondly, we have to use the access transistor
Now to use the access transistor. Word line should be one. so if word line is one. M is on now if M is on all the gain  depend on
Cs capacitor.
If there is a charge or let's say there is a voltage of one  then it will share the voltage here at this point since the voltage here is VDD by 2  and if it  share
the voltage.
The collector voltage would be greater than VDD by 2 and if this is present at the data line then it is send to sense amplifier futher
now this sense amplifier will say if the data line voltage is greater than VDD by 2 then the output is one
what if the voltage is less than VDD by 2 then this sense amplifier will say output is equal to zero and after doing this it will
refresh the cell
so we have to refresh this cell so this is the read operation
now let's move to write operation
so the second point we have is the write operation now we have to understand
in read operation, this data line acted as the output
so in write operation, this data line will act as input line. Now if this is the input line
We can place one or zero here. if we place one
This means that this capacitor would have the value 1. so this capacitor will be charged if we place a zero here then what will happen this capacitor will be discharged
so the value will be 0 so this is simple Data line will be acted as input line
Then word line should be 1 so we can access this transistor
because we can access this transistor that is if this is one we can access this capacitor
now so word line is one this mean that we
can access this capacitor now
and if word line is one then the voltage share
will be data line is one. Capacitor will have the voltage VDD
And if data line is zero then capacitor will
have the voltage zero.
So this is charging
this is discharge simple?