these sessions topic is memory chip
organization how the memory it may be
RAM may be ROM how this memory have
got fabricated how these chip
organizations are being made so actually
we are having two categories for that
one is a 2d organization and the another is the 2 and half D organization
so let me discuss them one by one I'm
having the suitable diagram with me so I
shall discuss with my diagrams so now
this is my 2d organization and this one
is my 2 and half D  the organization and
what are the advantages disadvantages
where I should go for 2d and 2 and half D organization
I should discuss everything here in this
session so now you see this is a decoder
let us suppose it is having 3 bits as
input you know that decoder is the
combinational circuit which will have n
number of input lines including the
power of n number of output lines and
depending upon the combination of the
input one of the output lines will be
selected at a time that that is the
basic and fundamental logic of a decoder
circuit so here we are having 3 input
lines and we are having eight output
lines at here so depending upon the
input bit combination one of the output
lines will be enabled and with the
particular output line we're having say
eight vertical lines we were having say in
eight vertical lines are there so now what
will happen so it might be eight might
be sixteen might be 24 so that is not
dependent on this decoder side so the
word that means word means the number of
bits in this particular line will be
coming out through this i/o circuit
whether the bits will be coming out or
going in obviously that will be decided
by this control line read or write so if
the control line is enable for read then
the data will be coming out through the
data to the data lines and if it is
writes then it'll be going in to the
respective word to be written to get
overwritten so that is the issue so
we're here we are having to develop of n
number of words if we have n
of select lines in this decoders input
so 2 ^ n number of words and you can
have M number of N and M they are not
related so M number of output lines
through this column IO circuit we know
that for the memory read and memory
write we are having two registers one is
called memory address registered in
short MAR and the other one is your memory
data registered in short it is MDR while
performing read operation MAR will be
containing the address from the MAR the
address will be coming to the decoder
input the respective world will get
selected depending upon the combination
and the output does obtained if I select
it in the read mode will be coming to
the MDR  memory data register in case
of memory write the MAR will be
containing the target memory locations
address so from the address from the
address register that means from the
MAR  memory address register the address
will be coming to the decoders input
respective word will get selected and
here I shall put the right control mode
enabled and then these data lines
through these data lines the respective
bits will be going to the respective
word to get written so in this way the
memory read and memory write will take
place for 2d organization
so let us come to the 2 and half D next
so in cases of 2 and half D organization
we are having the same kind of scenario
but here we are having some column bits
so in the column also we are having one
decoder so in the column also we are
having one decoder not the column IO
circuit so depending upon the bits in
the input and depending upon the bits in
this particular decoders input so one of
the output lines will get selected and
one of the output lines will get
selected let us suppose it will select
this particular cell to select this
particular cell so this line has got
enabled and say this line has got
enabled so this particular location has
got selected so from that very location
I should
that it is a bit position  at
the junction of these two one is the one
is the row line row line another one is
the column line so at the intersection
we are having one bit
so at that very bit position this
read/write control line will decide
whether I am writing then through
between the bit will come and that will
be written here if this control line
selects I'll be going for the reading
operation then from this bit the data
will be coming out that data bit will be
coming out to this bit output line so
what will happen each and every location
will contain a single bit so now how
many words do require how many bits of
word per location 64 so 64 such
parallel circuits will be working 32 32
such parallel circuits will be working
so now let us go for the comparisons
here the number of column output lines
are fixed hardware fixed but here how
many bits were going to get against a
single word that we shall we shall
decide because that number of circuits
will be working in parallel and here you
see the full address bits will be
divided into two part so this is some
bits will be coming down here some bits
will be coming down here so say we are
having 6 bits address so 3 bits here and
3 bits here
so six bits means how many combinations
6 bits means 64 combinations so 3 bits
means how many rows 8 rows 3 bits means
how many columns 8 columns so 8 rows and
8 columns so how many Junction points 64
so in this way you are getting the 64
but here all the 6 bits will be
applicable here so 64 horizontal lines
will be coming out so it will it will be
equating more complicated hardware
compared to this one so that is one
advantage second advantage here you see
I told you that it will be
requiring less Hardware less circuitry
less geeks next advantage point is
that here in this particular circuit as
we are having lesser number of hard
words and
logic gates and so on so the pin the IC
pin will be lesser number so easy to
implement easy to implement easy to
fabricate and next one is that here we
are getting from each and every circuit
we are getting a single bit depending
upon the row number and the column
number we are getting a single bit so
error correction code can be very much
applicable on these on this and you can
do the corrections we can further go for
the rejections we can go for the
collections individually for each if
every bit that is not possible here
because you are getting all these bits
in a bulk and the last one is that the
main difference I'm going to
tell you for most of the ROM circuits
we go for this 2d organization and in
the current trend in the most of the RAM
circuits will be going for two and half
D memory organization so that is the
issue so two and half D memory
organization for most of the RAM
circuits and 2D organization for
most of the your ROM circuits so this is
the memory chip organization so in this
particular session we have discussed 2d
and 2 and Half D the memory organization in
case of 2d all the address bits will be
applicable to the input of this column
sorry row wise decoder here the address
bits will be divided into two parts and
some of them will be applicable to the
row wise decoder and some of them will
be applicable to the column wise decoder
respectively a single cell will be
selected from the single cell I shall be
getting a single bit in or out depending
upon the read write mode through this
bit  and bit outlines and in this way
this sort of circuits will be working in
parallel for the multiple bits word size
so I think that your conception is
cleared draw these circles you know the
exam copies if such question come in
future thanks for watching