Nand based ROM Array when one input is low on
row 2 ,3 and 4 inputs are high
when the row input is low the N Mos
transistor corresponding to Row 1 in
column 2 or 4 will be turned off
therefore column 2 and column 4
outputs will be tied to VDD since Row 2
3 and 4 inputs are high the N Mos
transistor in column 1 and 3
correspondent to row 2 ,3 and 4 will be turn
on therefore column 1 and column 3
outputs will be tied to low row 2 input
is low row 1 3 and 4 inputs
are high when the row 2input is low the
N Mo's transistor correspondent row 2in
column 3 and 4 will be turned off
therefore column 3 and column 4
outputs will be tied to VDD since row
1 3 and 4 inputs are high the N Mo's
transistor in column 1 and 2
corresponding to Row 1 3 and 4 will be
turn on therefore column 1 and column
2 outputs will be tie to low row 3 input is low and row 1 2 and 4 inputs
are high when the row 3 input is low
the N Mos transistor correspondent or
row 3 in column 1 and 4 will be turned
off therefore column 1 and column 4
outputs will be tied to VDD since Row
1 2 and 4 inputs are high the N Mo's
transistor in column 2 and 3
corresponding to Row 1 2 and 4 will be
turn on therefore column 2 and column
3 outputs will be tie to low row 4
input is low and row 1 2 and 3 inputs
are high when the row for input is low
the N Mo's transistor corresponding to
Row 4 in column 2 and 3 will be turned
off therefore column 2 and column 3
outputs will be tied to VDD
since row 1 , 2and 3 inputs are
high the N Mos transistor in column 1
and 4 correspond in row 1, 2and
will be turn on therefore column 1 and
column 4 outputs will be tie to low
in another words to determine the column
outputs we can first to attach a row
with low input followed by checking the
presence or absence of an N Mos
transistor in the columns corresponding
to the row with low input the column
output will be high if the row input is
low and then N Mos transistor are present
in the column the column output will be
low if the row input is low and N Mos
transistor are absent in the column