Nor Based ROM Array when row 1 input is
high in row 2 3 & 4 inputs are low when
the row input is high the N Mos
transistor corresponding to row 1 in
column 1 and 3 will be turned on
therefore column 1 and column 3 outputs
will be tie to low since row 2,  3 and
4 inputs are low the N Mo's transistor
in column 2 and 4 corresponding to Row 2
3 & 4 will be turned off therefore
column two and column 4 outputs will be
tied to VDD
row 2 input is high and row 1 3 & 4
inputs are low when the row 2 input is
high the N Mo's transistor correspondent
row 2 in column 1 and 2 will be turn om
therefore column 1 and column 2 outputs
will be tie to low
since row 1 3 & 4 inputs are low
N Mos transistor in column 3 & 4
corresponding to Row 1 3 & 4 will be
turned off
therefore column 3 and column 4 outputs
will be tie to VDD Row 3 input is high
Row 1 2 & 4 inputs are low
when the row 3 input is high the N Mos
Mo's transistor corresponding to row 3
in column 2 & 3 will be turn on
therefore column two and column 3
outputs will be tie to low since row 1
2 & 4 inputs are low the N Mo's
transistor in column 1 & 4 corresponding
to Row 1 2 & 4 will be turned off
therefore column 1 and column 4 outputs
will be tied to VDD  row 4 input is
high and row  1 2 & 3 inputs are low
when the row 4 input is high the N
Mo's transistor corresponding  to row 4
in column 1 and 4 will be turn on
therefore column 1 and column 4
outputs will be tie to low since row
1 2 and 3 inputs are low the N
Mo's transistor in column 2 and 3
corresponding to row 1 2 and 3 will
be turned off therefore column 2 and
column 3 outputs will be tied to VDD
in another words to determine the
column outputs we can first to look at
row with high input followed by checking
the presence or absence of n Mo's
transistor in the columns corresponding
to the row with high input the column
output will be low if the row input is
high and then N Mos transistor are
present in the column the column output
will be high if the row input is high
and then N Mos transistor are absent in
the column