introduction to lab 14 semiconductor
memory in this video we'll explore the
concept of memory and the different
types you will encounter in this class
memory is a type of circuit used to
store electronic data memory cells are
tiny circuits existing in a larger chip
that store one bit of binary data each
the chips that exist in the multi sim
platform are able to store thousands of
bits worth of data memory chips can
usually read and write writing is a
process where data is stored in groups
of memory cells called words words
consist of bits ^ 2 ie
2 4 8 16 bits etc each word has a memory
address which acts like a marker so that
they can be identified when they need to
be read when a chip reads it recalls the
data stored in a word there are
increasing technologies and methods that
exist to reduce the time needed to read
data for example the memory in CDs can
only be read in the order in which it
was written even though this process
takes a matter of nanoseconds others are
even more efficient some of the newer
technologies include RAM random access
memory which can be both written read
and the memory accessed in any order
some forms of semiconductor memory can
only be read and not written these are
known as read-only memory or ROM some
examples of roms are proms programmable
read-only memory and eeproms
electrically erasable programmable
read-only memory in this lab you will
explore the functions of a word
generator and how these influence the
functionality of RAM