at the core of every computer are
devices that actually perform the
computations in most modern computers we
either use an Mos and P Mos
transistors as the base of most of our
operations and in this lecture we'll be
focusing on how we use these two gate RS
transistors to create logic gates
now this is the N Mos transistor itself
inside this circle and we have some
dimensions of how we use it so we
connect this lower terminal terminal 2
to ground it's sufficient just so you
know that this is the convention and you
can explore why in future courses and
then we have a gate which is our inputs
and that's how we control the transistor
from our perspective and that'll be a0
or a1 and then this terminal 1 connects
to other gates or the output of our
logic gate and then we've got our P Mos
transistor over here which behaves in a
opposite fashion we have our our
transistor here and notice this little
symbol that tells us this is the p MOS
transistor and we connect Terminal one
here to this high voltage VDD which is
usually like about 1 volt but that's
going to be varied based on the
technology and then we have our input
gate which allows us to control this
transistor and then terminal 2 connects
out to other circuits or other logic
gates and so how do we actually
make these work and what do these
actually do and so basically a
transistor is a electrically controlled
switch if we put a 1 in or a high
voltage the N Mos becomes a closed
circuit whereas the P MOS becomes an
open circuit and if we were to switch
off let's expose the second longer so
when this is closed or shorted there's a
direct path from ground up to here so
basically our output terminal has a 0
volt output
whereas this guy since there's a an open
circuit there's no current or anything
going through this and so this is just
basically a dangling wire there's
nothing there's nothing not connected to
anything however if we switch our inputs
the entire behavior changes our N mos
becomes an open and our PMos becomes a
short and so now there's a direct path
between our output and VDD so now this
is going to be our high voltage VDD and
keep altering these behaviors
being alternating between zero and once
and because they have opposite
functionality we call them complementary
and complementary mos or CMOS is how
we talk about NMOS and PMos as a group
and any other type of logic that has a
similar functionality the amazing thing
is that we can use just a PMos and NMOS
transistors to create any circuit and so
here we have a not gate and we'll show
you how this works if we have an input
of 0
our p-type is going to become a short
and directly connect the output to VDD
so when output is zero volts our output
what's going to have VDD volts which is
a logical one on the other hand this
this n-type is going to be open so
there's no connection between our output
and ground for if we input a 1 or VDD
volts we have a direct path between
ground and the output so our output is
going to have zero volts and be logical
zero and our p-type is going to become
an open so there's no connection between
VDD and the output and so this is how we
build our not gate which has this symbol
when we build more complicated or
complex digital logic circuits it
becomes important to notice there's
another part of what makes these guys
complimentary so down here n MOS
transistors are connected in series
that means the output of one is
connected as a terminal of the other
whereas our PMos up here are connected
in parallel where both of their outputs
are connected together and they're both
connected on their terminals to VDD and
these differing paths this parallel
path vs. series path is really important
that any time you have a PMos in
parallel you need to have an N Moss in
series they have a P Mos in series you
have an N Mos in parallel and that's
how we build our logic gates so that we
maintain this complementary
functionality now let's look at what
this circuit actually does
so let's input a 0 B  0 so an a is
0 this p MOS is going to be a short and
when B is 0 this p MOS is going to be a
short as well and so both these connect
our output directly to VDD so our output
should be a 1 and down here our a is
connected to our n MOS so that's going
to become an open and B is going to be
connect to this n Moss and create an
open so there's no path between ground
and the output so indeed our output is 1
and let's try another input
combination so let's try with 0 1 and
when a is 0 we're gonna have a short on
this p MOS just like before and with b
is 1 this is going to create an open on
this p MOS a with 0 is going to create
an open on this n MOS and b equal 1
is going to create a short so here our
ground is still cut off from the output
but we do have a direct path from VDD
down to the output so output is
going to be 1 now let's try the next
combination 1 0 this is going to be
exactly like the
for except a little bit flipped so a is
going to result in this being open this
B is going to cause us to be short and
then this a is going to cause this n mos
to be shorted and this B with 0 is
going to cause us and must to be open so
again there's no path between ground in
the output but there will be a path
between VDD and the output so the output
is 1 all right one last combination to
go we got a is 1 B is 1 that means a is
going to be an open on this p mos B
is going to be an open on this P Moss
and then a is going to result in a short
on this N Mos and B is going to
result in a short on this N mos so
now we have a path between ground and
the output so our output is 0 and we
have no paths between VDD and the output
so that reinforces that this is a 0 if
you recognize this truth table you
should recognize that this is the NAND
function the not and which has the
following circuit symbol we can now use
this NAND gate that we constructed to
create a NAND gate if we just concatenate
this not afterwards so we've got
our NAND and this is our not and this
would result in a B is our inputs C is our
outputs for a NAND gate this is one
reason why we tend to use only NAND
gates in our implementation of actual
computers because an and gate is a lot
more complicated well anyways we'll find
out more about that in future lectures
as well so let's look at one last
circuit and I'll just give the punchline
away for this one this is nor gate and
we'll see exactly how this behaves I
want to draw attention back to these the
series versus parallel here our p MOS
are in series whereas our n MOS
down on the bottom here are in parallel
because they share that common point
over here and so that we should
hopefully reinforce the idea that we
always do things complementarily
p mos and n Mos so let's look at the
inputs when  a is 0 B is 0 a creates a
short on the PMos B creates a short on
this PMos and then the a comes around
here and creates an open on the n MOS
and B creates an open on this N Mos
so we have a direct connection between
VDD and the output and no path between
ground and the output so output is 1
let's try the next simple combination
with 0 1 0 creates a short here and an
open here so there's no path between VDD
and the output and then we've got 0 over
here so this guy's becomes an open but
the B being one here  up short for
this N Mos so we have a path directly
from ground to the output so that
creates a 0 output next in book
combination 1 0 B is 1 so we have a open
here and a short on this P Mos because
of the B and then this guy is going to
be open and this guy will be shorted so
now we have a different path but we
still have a path nonetheless from
ground to the output so our output be 0
and then we put both these as 1 both of
our P Mos will be open and both of
our n Mos will be shorted so we have
two paths from ground to the output so C
will be 0 and our output will be 0 and
this again creates a nor gate which has
the circuit symbol nor and we can
combine nor with not to create or and
just like our NAND we generally will
refer to use nor gates exclusively in
our designs rather than using and OR
and NOT