in this video we are going to say
channel length modulation in short form
it is called CLM of a MOSFET Before we
jump into channel and modulation we will
first see how the characteristics of our
N channel enhancement MOSFET were in
different situations this is how the ID
versus VDS characteristics of a MOSFET
were when Vgs was equal to a constant
value let say which is Vgs 1 so I've
drawn these figures taking medius is
fixed which is VGs 1 and the first
figure represents when VDS is positive
and it is small so in that case we had
the entire channel and the current that
was flowing was somewhere here for the
given VDS which is very small and the
current was increasing linearly coming
to the second situation where VDS was
increased as the potential was higher on
the drain side there was reverse bias
and depletion region increased and the
channel thickness reduced or the
concentration of electrons in the
channel reduced due to which the
resistance increased and of course
potential increased hence we had current
increasing at a rate which is less
compared to this region and then when we
move on to a point where VDS was equal
to Vgs 1 minus Vth which was in fact
called the overdrive voltage when we
applied that potential so the potential
here was equal to Vgs 1 minus Vth in
which case the channel gets pinched off
so we have seen till this point we said
that the channel wouldn't allow any
extra current to flow beyond the current
that is flowing and pinch off hence we
took the characteristics to be constant
beyond the spins of point but in reality
the current beyond this overdrive
voltage is not going to be constant as
we discussed so now we will see why this
current wouldn't be constant beyond the
overdrive voltage of VDS let's say
says about the VGs 1 minus Vth
let's say we have some voltage here now
the question is what will happen to this
channel let's just say we have we apply
a potential by increasing this beyond we
Vgs 1 minus vth what'll happen is here
the potential wouldn't be Vgs1
minus Vth it will be this value if the
potential is this value here as the
potential increases from source to drain
there should be a point at which the
potential should become Vgs 1 minus
Vth along the channel in which case at
that point the channel should get
pinched off and if you take that
scenario and draw the figure this is how
it'll look where we are assuming the
potential that is applied that VDS is
greater than Vgs 1 minus vth which is
plus let's say the Delta V I am taking
that this is the point at which the
potential across the channel would
become Vgs 1 minus vth which means
this Delta V would be dropping across
this point where the entire channel here
is completely pinched off in this case
if you look at the channel it looks as
if the channel is existing only till
this point when we started we assumed
the channel length is L but now the
channel length seems to be reduced
because of the extra voltage that we
applied beyond the overdrive voltage in
this case what would happen is the
electrons that are coming from source to
drain when they enter into this pinched
off region the electrons would get
accelerated because we have applied a
potential which is higher now which
means the electric field should be
higher compared to this scenario so the
electrons that actually come here let's
say the Delta V potential is getting
dropped here and at this point at this
point the potential would be Vgs 1 minus
Vth in the channel now electrons when
they get accelerated which means the
rate of flow of carriers would increase
now assuming the velocity of the
electrons haven't come to the saturation
velocity in which case the current would
increase as we increase the potential so
hence the current should actually be
increasing beyond overdrive voltage and
it is not going to be
constant like this so let me show that
particular curve here which would look
like this
the curve in the red color but of course
these two curves are for a fixed Vgs
which is which is Vgs1 now why is this
called channel length modulation because
if you look at here the channel seems to
be this value which is less than the
actual channel length now as we increase
this potential beyond even this value
this point would move here which means
from here onwards it will be like this a
single line kind of but if you reduce
this potential this point would move to
here which means the channel length here
would be actually getting more related
increasing and decreasing with respect
to the drain to source potential hence
it is called the channel length
modulation so let me say this is with CL
m and this is without CL m in fact this
point remains we offer the Tom Cruise
movie which is night and day in which he
says with me without me with me without
me in this case we can say this is with
CLM the current is higher without CLM
the current is less with CLM without
CLM
now let's find out how would the current
equation be with channel and modulation
to find out first I'm taking the
current equation in saturation region
without CLM now we know that the
channel length has reduced so we're
going to take the L is equal to L Prime
in fact L prime is equal to L minus
Delta L of course this Delta L is a
function of VDS that why it is called
channel length modulation so this can be
written equal to L taking common 1 minus
Delta L over L which is normalized value
here and of course this Delta L over L
will be directly proportional to VDS so
we can equate this with a
proportionality constant called lambda
times VD s so this can be equated again
as L times 1 minus lambda Vds
we will substitude this value here in
which case I D would be equal to mu Cox
prime W by L so L is written as L times
1 minus lambda VDS so this will be in
the denominator I am going to take this
in the numerator so that it becomes 1
minus lambda VDS power minus 1 1 minus
lambda VDS power minus 1 times Vgs minus
Vth
whole square over 2 taking lambda times
VDS is very less than 1 we can rewrite
this expression where if you see lambda
units would be volt inverse because this
is normalized even this entire time
should be unitless if this is volt this
is volt inverse hence we should not be
having unit lambda is volt inverse so
this is equal to ID times 1 plus lambda
VDs where ID is a current without
channel length modulation so let's put
this this is ID of course this ID is
different so just for convenience I am
putting a prime here which is a modified
ID which is the drain current with
channel length modulation is equal to
the drain current of without channel and
modulation times 1 plus lambda VDS so
let me summarize here this is channel
length modulation and this is without
channel and modulation and of course
going forward I wouldn't be writing this
as ID prime simply I'll write ID is
equal to the entire equation