all chips start out with a very simple
raw material sand sand is primarily made
up of silicon dioxide or silica silicon
is the second most abundant element in
the Earth's crust but is only ever found
as a compound with oxygen complex
chemical and physical processes are
required to ensure that silicon crystals
meets the high production standards that
apply to chips to convert silica sand to
silicon the sand is combined with carbon
and heated to an extremely high
temperature to remove the oxygen a
number of other steps are required to
create the finished product namely an
extremely pure mono crystalline silicon
ingot called a bull with only one
impurity atom for every 10 million
silicon atoms silicon bulls are
fabricated in a range of different
diameters the most common sizes are 150
200 and 300 millimeters wafers with
large diameters offer more space for
chips
extremely thin wafers are then cut from
the silicon bulls using a special sawing
technique these wafers are the basic
building blocks for subsequent chip
production silicon is a semiconductor
this means it can conduct electricity
and also act as an insulator its atomic
structure looks like this every silicon
atom has four outer electrons there are
no free charge carriers as a result the
pure mono crystalline silicon is non
conductive at room temperature to allow
it to become conductive small quantities
of specific atoms are added as
impurities to the wafer these impurity
atoms must have a number of outer
electrons that is either one more or one
less than that of silicon silicon is in
the fourteenth group of the periodic
table of elements
this means that elements in the
thirteenth or fifteenth group have to be
used in this process referred to as
doping boron and phosphorus atoms are
the most suitable elements in these
groups they are very close to silicon on
the periodic table and therefore have
very similar properties phosphorus has
five outer electrons when it is inserted
into the silicon crystal lattice the
fifth phosphorus electron can move
freely this means that the silicon
phosphorus crystal is n conductive
in contrast boron atoms only have three
outer electrons when they are introduced
into the silicon lattice one silicon
electron has nothing to bond to this
creates electron holes the holes move
through the crystal like positively
charged particles making the material P
conductive transistors are built on the
P and n conductive layers that exists in
a doped wafer transistors are the
smallest control units and microchips
their job is to control electric
voltages and currents and they are by
far the most important components of
electronic circuits every transistor on
a chip contains P and n conductive
layers made of silicon crystals they
also have an additional layer of silicon
oxide which acts as an insulator a layer
of electrically conductive polysilicon
is applied on top of this every
transistor has three terminals the
middle one is attached to the gate which
is the electrically conductive
polysilicon
if an electrical charge is applied to
only the two outer terminals electricity
cannot flow as the transistor is blocked
this changes however if an additional
charge is applied to the middle terminal
electrons from the P layer are then
pulled toward the middle terminal and
accumulate at the area bordering the
silicon crystal and the insulating gate
oxide a channel then forms underneath
the gate between the islands of n
conductive material electrons can now
flow through this channel the electrical
circuit is closed in this way the
transistor can be switched back and
forth between current enable and disable
between zero and one on and off but how
are these layers created on a wafer the
process to manufacture chips from a
wafer starts with the layout and design
phase highly complex chips are made up
of billions of integrated and connected
transistors enabling sophisticated
circuits such as microcontrollers and
crypto chips to be built on a
semiconductor surface measuring just a
few square millimeters in size the sheer
number of components calls for an
in-depth design process this entails
defining the chips functions simulating
its technical and physical properties
testing its functionality and working
out the individual transistor
connections special design tools are
used to draw up the plans for integrated
circuits and develop a three-dimensional
architecture of sandwich layers
this blueprint is transferred to photo
masks providing geometric images of the
circuits the photo masks are used as
image templates during the subsequent
chip fabrication process to ensure that
the microscopic structures of a chip are
reproduced flawlessly they have to be
fabricated in a dust-free environment
with stable temperature and humidity
levels in other words they have to be
made in a cleanroom a cleanroom is a
room in which no more than one particle
of dust larger than 0.5 micrometers is
permitted in around 10 litres of air
this is even cleaner than the air in an
operating room
the ventilation filtration and supply
systems in a cleanroom
therefore have to be extremely
sophisticated several million cubic
meters of air are circulated every hour
and hundreds of air volume regulators
maintain a constant air flow employees
in these production areas have to abide
by an extremely strict dress code they
are not permitted to smoke before work
or wear any makeup or jewelry cleanroom
production areas can only be accessed
through a special airlock chips are
built on a base wafer cut from a silicon
pool depending on their size several
dozen or several thousand chips can be
fabricated on one wafer first of all the
surface of the wafer is oxidized in a
high-temperature furnace operating at
approximately 1,000 degrees Celsius to
create a non conductive layer then a
photoresist material is uniformly
distributed on this non conductive layer
using centrifugal force this coating
process creates a light-sensitive layer
the wafer is then exposed to light
through the photo mask in special
exposure machines known as steppers
during this process coaster sized areas
of the chip template known as recta
khals are used to transfer the complex
geometric patterns of the circuit design
to the silicon wafer the exposed area of
the chip pattern is developed revealing
the layer of oxide below the unexposed
part remains as is protecting the layer
of oxide after this the exposed layer of
oxide is etched off in the areas that
have been developed using wet or plasma
etching with plasma etching special
gases bond with the substrate to be
removed in the reaction chamber this
enables microscopic layers to be removed
in the windows that were exposed and
developed in the previous step once the
photoresist residue has been stripped
and the wafer has been cleaned the wafer
undergoes further oxidation electrically
conductive polysilicon is deposited on
this insulation layer then photoresist
is applied again and the wafer is
exposed to light through the mask the
exposed photoresist is stripped again
now the polysilicon and the thin oxide
layer are etched off these two layers
only remain intact in the centre under
the photoresist the next step is the
doping process where impurity atoms are
introduced into the exposed silicon and
ion implanter is used to shoot impurity
atoms into the silicon this changes the
conductivity of the exposed silicon by
fractions of a micrometer
after the photoresist residue has been
stripped
another oxide layer is applied the wafer
undergoes another cycle of applying
photoresist exposure through the mask
and stripping contact holes are etched
to provide access to the conductive
layers enabling the contacts and
interconnections to be integrated in the
wafer this is done by depositing metal
alloys onto the wafer in sputtering
machines
[Music]
once again the photoresist and masks are
applied the unexposed strips remain as
is after the etching process providing a
point of contact to the underlying
layers to give the insulation layer
above the interconnections the smooth
finish it requires a chemical mechanical
process is used to polish away excess
material with micrometer accuracy these
individual steps may be repeated
multiple times in the fabrication
process until the integrated circuit is
complete depending on the size and type
of chip the wafer will now contain
anything from several dozen to thousands
of chips individual chips are usually
sought out of the wafer the chips are
not lined up flush with each other on
the wafer because tiny parts of the
wafer splinter off during the sawing
process a certain amount of space known
as the scribe line is always left
between the individual chips test
structures are also integrated in the
space between the chips and used to take
measurements immediately after
production these tech structures are
destroyed during the sawing process
the size of the resulting chips
typically varies between one square
millimeter and a few square centimeters
the final stage of fabrication is
assembly here the individual chips are
placed in a package and terminals are
attached the result is a finished
semiconductor device which can be
mounted on circuit boards using
different types of terminals over a
thousand connection contacts can be
realized here are some examples of ready
packaged semiconductor components
special larger packages are used for
power semiconductors intended for
applications such as trains electric
cars solar panels and wind turbines
these power semiconductors are designed
to switch electrical currents of up to
several hundred amps and voltages that
run into the thousands switching at this
level generates high temperatures and
this heat has to be dissipated via
cooling areas integrated into the
packages here you can see some fully
packaged power semiconductors
cutting-edge technologies used for
testing at every step in the fabrication
process to ensure the highest quality
levels in chip yield researchers and
developers use scanning electron
microscopes to repeatedly check the
chips at different points in the
production process
if we compare today's micro electronics
with human hair we can see just how
small these devices are the equipment
used to check components and analyze
defects is just as precise these high
levels of precision and quality are
essential at every stage of the workflow
from the production of silicon bulls
through the cleaning room fabrication to
quality control in order to deliver
these tiny building blocks that have
such a big impact on our lives today and
in the future after all demand is rising
for innovative semiconductor solutions
that make life easier safer and greener
for technology that achieves more
consumes less and is available to
everyone
Micro Electronics is the key to a better
future part of your life part of
tomorrow Infineon