in this note we're going to talk about the
voltages that define different Mosfet
regions of operation
we'll start with an N mos device
we have the cutoff region
that is defined as the gate-to-source
voltage being less than the threshold
voltage for the device if the gate to
source voltage is less than the
threshold device we are operating in cutoff
for gate to source voltage greater than
the threshold voltage we have to check to
see if
the gate to source voltage minus the
threshold if the drain to source voltage
is greater than the gate to source
voltage minus the threshold so the
drain to source is greater than the gate
to source minus at threshold voltage the
device is in saturation
if the drain to source is less than the
gate to source
minus the threshold voltage the devices in
the triode or linear region now one
thing that we can do is know
the VDS
minus  VGS
must be greater than minus Vt
or if we multiply everything through by
a negative then we could write that the
VGS minus VDS is
must be less than VT
because the source is common to both vgs
and VDS we could also just write the Vgd
must be less than threshold voltage this
is the case and we're in saturation
otherwise
we are in triode/linear
when dealing with a p-mos device the
easiest thing to do is just reverse the
voltages on all these devices so for
instance we could write it for cut
off VSG
is less than absolute value of VT for a
P-mos device if the VSG is greater
than VT for P mos device then we need
to check the drain to source condition
so we could write VSD must be greater
than the VSG minus the absolute value of
the threshold voltage in this case we're
in saturation
if VSD is less than the VSG minus the absolute
value of the threshold voltage in the
device is in the triode or linear region
one other note we mentioned that the
channel capacitance is equal to Cox
times the width of the device times the
length I wanted it to be clear what we
meant by width and length so the length is
the length between the source
terminal
separated by the gate of the transistor
so this dimension is the length but width
is imagine if we sketch this device into
three dimensions the width is
that third dimension
now we also noted that Cox is equal
to eox / tox and this is the
capacitance per unit area for a device t
ox is the thickness of the oxide
and Eox is equal to
the permeability of free space times the
relativev permittivity of
the material in this case silicon
dioxide and our relative permittivity
for our permittivity of free space is
equal to 8.854 times ten to the minus
twelve farads per meter and the relative
permittivity of silicon dioxide is
approximately equal to four
so with all of those equations you
should now be able to solve for any Mos
device bias region