memory chip design is the first step in
the production of microns memory chips
this process involves the use of
computer aided design tools to lay out
billions of electronic components that
store data on the chip according to the
product design specification during
technology development specific process
steps are defined and integrated into a
process flow that will build the memory
chips the process steps are tested and
refined until the process note is
qualified and ramped in manufacturing
[Music]
individual memory chips or die
are built upon pure silicon wafers in a
fabrication area or fab Fab Tsar
state-of-the-art clean rooms that are
100 times cleaner than a hospital
operating room to ensure silicon wafers
are protected from ambient contamination
among the many process areas in a fab
the photolithography area coats wafers
with a photo resistant material then
like film and a camera circuit patterns
are exposed and excess material is
rinsed away the paths in these circuits
are 5,000 times narrower than a human
hair wafers are moved between different
tools and processes using a robotic
automated material handling system or a
MHS each wafer may be moved through more
than a thousand processes it takes more
than one month to make a memory chip
in probe initial functionality tasks are
performed on each die on the wafer a
probe card positions probe needles onto
each die to send and receive test data
this information is used to generate a
map of all the die on each wafer only
good die that pass all tests in probe
will continue through the manufacturing
process in assembly wafers are first
thinned attached to an adhesive backing
and then diced into individual die using
a diamond two-edged saw using the wafer
map that was created in probe individual
die are picked from the wafer then
placed on a circuit board a solid-gold
Winer is used to connect each chip to
the circuit board a molding process
encapsulate s' each die in a protective
plastic package and shipped to test
[Music]
every memory chip micron manufacturers
undergoes hundreds of tests to ensure it
meets the highest quality standards
proprietary an VIX testers subject
finished parts to extreme temperatures
and conditions to force any weak
components to fail before they reach our
customers additional test equipment
verifies that each part meets or exceeds
its speed and performance specifications
[Music]
all qualified parts are laser marked
with partners and other identifying
information each memory chip is
optically scanned to verify strict fit
and form specifications components are
placed into industry standard
anti-static packaging and placed into
boxes for shipment many of microns
finished parts are used to build memory
modules and solid-state drives
automated surface mount assembly
equipment is used to mount memory and
other components to printed circuit
boards all products are tested using
proprietary micron memory module and SSD
test equipment finished products are
placed into anti-static packaging before
boxing for shipment to the customer
[Music]