so in this video I'm going to be talking
about the MOSFET IV characteristics and
specifically I'm going to be talking
about what's called the long channel
model and what that means will hopefully
be clear in a second so I'm assuming
that you've you're taking a
semiconductor physics course and you
encountered this equation IDs equals mu
n si ox W over L times vgs minus VT
times VDS minus one-half VDS squared and
you're just thrown the equation were
just thrown at you maybe very briefly
they went over where it came from but
essentially they just throw it at you
and expect you to memorize it in this
video I'm gonna try to go over where
exactly this equation comes from and so
this is also known as MOSFET operating
in the triode region and so I'm gonna
try to describe the model behind where
this equation comes from and how we
actually arrive at it so it turns out
that the model is actually pretty scheme
pretty simple actually a scarily simple so
if we've got to say we've got a MOSFET
right here so this is going to be our
gate we've got some gates got some
thickness here so it's got some metal up
top probably copper or aluminum or
polysilicon let's just say it's a little
numb or something then we've got an
oxide which essentially protects the
gate or protects the rest of the MOSFET
from the gate and we've got our P
substrate our n + Wells this is a n Moss
MOSFET and so I'm assuming that you've
seen all this before and so the model
that we're going to use is basically
we're going to ignore
all the complicated stuff and just
pretend that we only care about this
region here the channel and specifically
we're assuming that the channel is just
comprised of a bunch of charges and here
they're assumes to be actually negative
charges because this is an NMOS
transistor so we've got a bunch of
negative charges piling up here and
we're interested in the current from the
source to the drain so we're interested
or typically we're interested in the
current from the drain to the source or
the electron flow from the source to the
drain IDs so we want an equation for
ideas we want IDs equals what what does
it depend on and I've already told you
the answer up here but how do we
actually get to that answer and how can
we remember that answer well we know
that a MOSFET behaves like a variable
capacitor right so if we've got a if we
apply a certain voltage to the gate
nothing happens
we're increasing the voltage nothing
happens nothing happens and then all of
a sudden we'll start to get these
carriers accumulate near the edge at a
certain threshold voltage so at VG and
we'll just say VG C because this is the
voltage relative to the channel or the
little portion of the substrate that we
care about so at VGC equals the
threshold voltage we start getting
charge accumulation at the interface so
we start getting negative charges piling
up here and positive charges piling up
on the gate now as we increase the
voltage on the gate there are always
charges piling up on the gate but the
p-type substrate has too many positive
charges such that the channel doesn't
actually look like it has any negative
charge so we have to overcome that
first so this is all that we're going to
use to derive this model we're gonna
assume that this MOSFET acts like a
capacitor and we know that the charge of
a capacitor is just equal to the
capacitance times the voltage except in
our case it takes a certain voltage
before the MOSFET starts acting like a
capacitor so we're gonna change this a
little bit we're gonna say that Q is
equal to the capacitance times some
voltage minus the threshold voltage and
so this is the equation that we're we're
going to start with well we're not
actually interested in the charge we're
interested in the current and how did
how do we relate the - well we know if
we've got say we've got a cube of charge
here and it's got some value Q we know
that the current so the current flowing
through some plane here the charge block
is just moving along minding its own
business
the current is just how long it takes
this block of charge to move through
this plane so it's the total charge
divided by the time that it takes and so
up until the charge block reaches the
reaches the plane we don't have any
current and then all of a sudden we
start having current as the as the
charge block transitions through the
through the plane well okay what is what
is the time it takes a charge block to
transition through the through the plane
well we know the the charge block has a
certain length to it right so and it's
got a certain velocity V so the time
that it takes is just the length divided
by the velocity well that's that's
fairly simple right so we can rearrange
our or plug that into our equation we
say that I is equal to Q or the total
charge of our block divided by L over V
or Q divided by L times V and V here is
the velocity so why don't we call this
like EQ of the velocity of the charge
block Q
well okay so from this from this where
do we go well if we want to know the
charge of a capacitor recall that we've
got a capacitor here we know that the
charge is just CV or as we said above C
V minus vthreshold so we can add that in
we've got the capacitance V minus
vthreshold divided by the length times
the velocity of the charge block and if
you've taken semiconductor physics
you'll know that Ohm's law on the
microscopic level just says that the
velocity of a given charge charged
particle is just equal to the mobility
times of that charged particle times the
electric field so we can replace that in
our equation we're starting to get
Chardonnay closer and I'm going to
replace this V with V G C the voltage
between the gate and the channel just so
it's clear what voltage we're talking
about and the reason I'm replacing this
V velocity as quickly as I can and so we
don't have multiple V's floating around
so that's equal to C VG minus VT times
the mobility times the electric field
divided by the length well okay you can
probably guess what we're gonna do next
we're gonna use another elementary
formula to figure out the rest of these
things so what is the capacitance what
is the electric field now we're assuming
that we know the mobility we're assuming
that we know the dimensions of this
thing so that those are the those the
only assumptions that we make well onto
capacitance so we know that the
capacitance of a parallel plate
capacitor that's filled with some
dielectric of permittivity epsilon we
know that the capacitance is just the
area times that epsilon divided by the
thickness or the distance between the
two plates here we call this t ox or the
thickness of the oxide because that's
the thickness of
capacitance or the dielectric that were
that were interested in and area we can
just rewrite as the width of the
transistor times the length of the
transistor so W times L times epsilon
divided by the thickness of the oxide
and so that's we just plug that back
into the equation so W times L times
epsilon divided by thickness of the
oxide and then we've got another L on
the bottom and then that's multiplied by
mu e times VG e or VG C minus VT and
sorry if the equation is starting to get
a little a little complicated we're
going to simplify it right now so first
these ELLs are going to cancel out and
we're going to group these these terms t
ox and epsilon into a single term C ox
or the in other words we're going to say
that the total capacitance is equal to C
ox times the area of the transistor or
the so C ox is a capacitance density if
you will it's the capacitance per unit
area of the device so if we cancel out L
we make that substitution we get our
formula W times C ox times mu e times V
G C minus VT and we're starting to get
closer see we've got a W we've got a mu
we've got a C ox we we still have this e
which we will want to get rid of and
we've got this awkward VGC because we we
don't know what VC is we don't the
channel isn't a terminal of the
transistor so let's let's see what else
we can do to this equation
well how about let's just attack this
first one e so what is the electric
field in the in the channel in terms of
what we know well if we go back to our
transistor we know that there's a source
on this side there's a drain on this
side or we can flip the sides if you
prefer and there's some voltage between
the two
VDS and we know just from basic
electromagnetics that the electric field
between two points in space if
everything is homogeneous and everything
works out everything works out nicely is
just equal to the voltage divided by the
distance between them which here is the
transistor length so we're assuming that
these wells are all at the same
potential well okay we can we can make
that substitution and then we get mu
times C ox times W and now we have the
over L that we were expecting which is
from our electric field times VD s times
VGC minus VT and we're almost done the
the only thing left is VG C so how do we
how do we figure out what VG c is well
if we look at our MOSFET again this is
VC so we've got a we've got a certain
gate voltage that we apply right VG and
we've got a channel voltage here VC and
then we also know there's a source
voltage here V s and a drain voltage
here V D and you know if we just make
some some somewhat sketchy arguments
like say pretend there's two resistors
here and there's some current flowing
through this eye then we know that VC is
and let's say these resistors are the
same value and this is you know fairly
realistic because the material itself is
going to have a resistance so we we know
that this point VC has to be the
midpoint between V s and VD that's just
a basic voltage divider so we can
rewrite VC VC is just V s plus VD over
du or it's the midpoint and now we just
need to perform some algebraic wizardry
which all all that ever amounts to in
engineering is subtracting or adding one
or subtracting or adding a zero from an
equation so
we're gonna say VC is equal to vs over
two plus VD over two and then we're
going to add zero and the reason we're
gonna add zero is so we can rearrange
this equation make it nice and pretty
we're going to add V s over 2 minus 3 s
over 2
ok so rewriting the full equation this
is this is going to be our almost our
final form IDs is equal to MU n and this
so this is mu of the electrons see ox W
over L times when we had a VD s and then
VG C which is VG minus VC which is V s
over 2 plus V s over 2 that's BS VD over
2 so plus VD over 2 and then there was
another minus V s over 2 and then minus
the threshold voltage VT I might have
forgotten that up there as well okay so
all we need to do is group things and
rearrange them so mu n SI ox W over L
times VD s times VG minus V s which is
just VG s plus one half and now we're
going to group this VD and this V s plus
1/2 V SD or we can rewrite that as minus
1/2 VD s minus 1/2 VD s minus VT and
then all we need to do is factor this VD
s into all these terms and we're done
and we have our final equation for a
MOSFET which is the drain current mu n
si ox W over L times vgs minus VT times
VDS minus 1/2 VDS squared and so that's
sort of where the equation comes from
that's the that's the derivation for it
I hope you found this video interesting
and hopefully not too mathematical and
we're kind of able to follow along with
what we're doing I strongly suggest that
you you try to do this yourself because
the thinking process behind it is the
same thinking process behind basically
all of engineering so hope you enjoyed
it