let us discuss MOSFET in detail
MOSFET is an electronic device most
widely used in ICs it has three
terminals named as source drain and gate
construction of basic design of MOSFET
is quite simple just take a block of
p-type semiconductor this block will be
your base for MOSFET we also call it as
substrate and the entire MOSFET we will
fabricate on this base now two portions
on the same side of this p-type
substrate are made highly doped with
n-type impurity as these are shown here
in the figure source and drain terminals
are brought out from these two end
regions as shown
now the entire surface of the substrate
is coated with a layer of silicon
dioxide silicon dioxide will behave here
as insulation on this layer of silicon
dioxide a thin metallic plate is placed
this metallic plate will act as gauge
contact to the substrate the gate
terminal is brought out from this
metallic plate
hence it is seen from the figure that
gate contact is insulated from the
substrate but drain and source contacts
are directly connected to respective
n-type regions
this was the constructional feature of a
buzz FET now we will come to the
operational features of MOSFET
for that we have to connect on DC
voltage source between these two n-type
regions
you
the n-type region connected with
positive terminal of the source is
called as drain and the N region
connected with negative terminal of the
source is called as source as soon as
the drain and source are connected with
DC voltage source there will be two PN
junctions formed one is in between
n-type drain and p-type base
and the other is in between P type base
and n type source as drain is connected
with positive terminal of the source the
drain is in higher voltage than base
hence this PN Junction is reverse biased
on the other hand as source is connected
with negative terminal of the battery P
type base will be at higher potential
than n type source
hence this PN Junction is forward biased
as between drain and source there will
be one reverse biased and one forward
biased Junction there will be no
significant current flowing from the
drain to source but a tiny current
continues to flow due to minority
carriers we can say that virtually there
is no continuous path or channel between
drain and source
now let us see what happens if one
suitable positive voltage is applied at
gate terminal of the device
in that case due to attraction a
positive potential of gate contact plate
negative free electrons that is minority
carriers in p-type base
we'll be accumulated towards a contact
plate and form a channel of negative
charge carriers even inside p-type
semiconductor
this channel due to higher concentration
of free electrons will behave as n-type
semiconductor
although entire base is doped with P
type or trivalent impurity it is obvious
that the number of free electrons
accumulated towards gate contact plate
depends on the strength a positive
potential given to the gate terminal
hence width of n channel depends on the
voltage applied at gate terminal more
the applied voltage greater the width of
the channel means greater the
conductance between drain and source
here we have seen that there is no
direct connection between gauge contact
and substrate instead these are
insulated from each other but due to
electrostatic attraction the conducting
channel between drain and source is
formed and because of that the channel
is also called induced shadow and the
device is called induced channel MOSFET
it is also clear that when there is no
voltage applied to the gate of the
device there will be no current from
drain to source except negligible amount
of saturation current due to minority
carriers but if the gate voltage is
gradually increased by keeping fixed
drain to source voltage after certain
minimum applied gate voltage drain to
source current will start flowing
and this voltage is called threshold
voltage
so below threshold voltage the device
will behave as non conducting or in off
board
and for gate voltage greater than
threshold value the device will be in
conducting or on mode
so this type of MOSFET is suitably used
as a gate control switching device
thank you