Hello guys here. We will learn the next step
of the feedback amplifier videos that is nothing
but feedback topologies and the feedback typologies
We should know that how
many feedback amplifiers we have. We have
learned the voltage current transconductance
transresistance amplifier and based on that.
We will learn how many feedback topology is.
We have and on which basis we will classify
these feedback topologies. As far as this
topologies  are concerned. This topologies
are based on two factors how I am sampling
that particular output voltage with which
parameter and how am mixing that particular
voltage or current with particular parameter
with your input parameter, right? So depending
on that I will classify these typologies.
So before declassification, we should most
we should know that what is Sampling and what
is mixing? Okay, so we'll learn first. What
is sampling and what is mixing? So sampling
is nothing but let us understand the fact
that here we will say. This is your forward
block A okay, which is nothing but having
gained A and here I am saying it's having
two part one is ground and one with respect
to particular voltage or current right and
I can say that here it is your feedback. This
is B okay what I'm saying that This particular
node a is joint with this particular node
B and this whatever rest node, which is attached
to this right then. Can you imagine can you
tell me that which part which parameter of
the output voltage is sampled? Whether it
is of current whether it is a voltage, right?
We have only two parameters to sample right
one is voltage and one is current now here
we can easily say that. If this is A and this
is B, right, what is the voltage between voltage
at the output side for forward block right
voltage at the output for the forward block
is nothing but VA minus VB, right? So VA
minus VB is nothing but the output voltage
which is at the forward amplifier right now.
I can say that whether current is given as
the sampled or voltage is given as a
sample parameter right current is flowing
through this particular part, right which
is given here right now current is also flowing
through this particular part, which is given
over here, right? But here I can say that
the value of the current will be different
because your load resistance is attached over
here. This is your RL, right? I can say
what if whatever voltage which is been given
at the input side is also same as that of
the output voltage of the forward block amplifier,
right? I can say this is nothing but the voltage
sampling. Okay, so I can say this is called
as the sampling. This is basically the sampling
Now we will learn what how I will get the
voltage sampling and how I will get the current
sampling. Okay. So sampling sampling is nothing,
but the part of output feed to input of
feedback circuit That is called as sampling
so we have two sampling part one is voltage
sampling. And another is current sampling.
Okay, so we will learn quickly. How will get
the voltage sampling and how will get the
current sampling? Okay.So first of all, I
will draw this circuit where I will get the
voltage sampling. This is A this is B part,
which is nothing but the feedback this is
forward block and I can say this complete.
Voltage at the output side is nothing but
the input side of your feedback block.Okay
here I can say that this is nothing but your
output voltage Vo and this is also the output
voltage Vo so I can say that voltage is fed
back to your feedback circuit, and that's
why it is called as voltage sampling. So the
sampling part is voltage sampling now, how
will I get the different part which is nothing
but your current sampling how the circuit
will change at the output side. So we'll say
that. Let's draw the circuit again. Now I
can say that whatever current which is been
given right that is forwarded to your output
part. Right so I can say that this is how
the series combination will give you the current
sampling. So here I can say this is nothing
but the current Io and that is nothing but
the current Io. So obviously naming part
is as usual A and B. forward and feedback block
and I can say that this is achieved as current
sampling. Well giving all the number current
for each and every feedback topologies This
part is very very important whenever I am
using this shunting Network. So we'll say
that shunt circuit. Okay, this is shunt circuit
and this is the nothing but the series if
you can see here from the output side
of the forward block and input side of the
feedback block is connected in series so I
can say this is nothing but the series circuit.
Okay. So keep this words in your mind while
defining particular topologies name. So as
far as sampling is concerned sampling is done
at the output side of the negative feedback
amplifier.Now we will learn what is the another
part that is called as mixing Okay, so We
will say that what is mixing mixing is nothing
but the addition. or subtraction of feedback
signal with source signal is called as mixing.
Okay, that is also been different thing. You
say that this is a mixer. Okay, and here I
can say that. Things are added. This is your
A and this is B okay. This can be your
current. This can be your voltage. Okay, I
have to identify that when it will be current
sample. Even it will be current to be mixing
when it will be voltage mixing. Okay, so we
will see how it will be having the current
mixing and how it will be having the voltage
mixing. Usually it is called as series mixing
or shunt mixing but all together we are adding
some parameter and depending on the addition
of that particular parameter. We will say
that it is a series mixing or shunt mixing.
So here we will generalized in the form of
mixing. So keep this in mind that mixing is
been done in the negative feedback at the
input side of the negative
feedback amplifier. So we will learn how we
will be getting the voltage mixing was  similarly with
current mixing we will learn that later
on. So how will I add the voltages? So if
this is the complete Source voltage okay with
respect to ground and I'm saying this is your
input voltage. This is your input voltage.
This is your Source voltage and this is your
Feedback voltage. So this is input voltage.
This is your feedback voltage and this is
your Source voltage. Can I identify that?
What is the relation between VI , VF and Vs.
Yes easily. I can say that Vs is nothing
but the addition of VI and VF okay, I can
say that this is Possible only if voltage
addition Is Possible only if the two circuits
are in series right? So if They're in series
connection then and only then it is possible
to have the addition of the two voltage becomes
your value of Vs is equal to VI plus VF.
Okay, so that's why we can name this mixing
part as your series mixing. So we have done
with the mixing voltage mixing part and it
is also called as series mixing. Okay, so
we will learn the another part as current
mixing how current will get mixed at the input
side. Okay, so we'll draw the particular diagram
for that. Now here I can say that. This is
the current I-s right. And at this node, this
current is getting divided into two parts
one is current I-i and one is current I-f Okay,
we'll decide that direction later on but keep
this in mind that at this particular load
I-s is getting divided into two part I-i and
I-f right by using KCl and this is Possible
only if I Can use the shunt configuration.
So that's why this current mixing is also
called as shunt mixing. So whenever I am using
this current of your feedback voltage of feedback
output signal current is in the form of current
and that current is getting added with your
Source current. Then I can say that it forms
your shunt mixing, right? So as far as the mixing
and sampling part is considered we have learned
for configuration one is current sampling
voltage. Current mixing and voltage mixing
as far as voltage sampling is concerned. It
is also called as shunt circuit as far as
current sampling is also called as it is also
called as a series sampling,but when I'm dealing
with the mixing part, it is been done at the
input side of the negative feedback amplifier.
So voltage mixing is also called as a series
mixing and your current mixing is also called
as a shunt mixing so there will be two names
whether it is of the sampling mixing type
or mixing sampling types. So we learn
that topologies now now here we will go for
the particular types of topologies. So let's
discuss the particular types of topologies.
First topology, we will learn what will happen
if I'm using the circuit which will give you
voltage sampling and series mixing. Okay,
so that is called as voltage series. negative
feedback amplifier It's a long name voltage
series negative feedback amplifier. So it
is also have some different name. I'm saying
that this all naming is been done by using
sampling mixing type that means at the output
side to input side. So I'm saying that this
is using sampling mixing type I will use
all the names by using sampling and mixing
type. Okay now tell me how will I use another
name if I'm using current sampling and series
mixing. Okay, so that will be your current.
Series negative feedback amplifier.I'm using
the same notation sampling and mixing. So
the name itself will tell you that what is
the sampling sampling parameter is current
and how the parameter is added. It is in series
combination, right? So third one will be voltage
shunt parameter where you are sampling parameter
is voltage and the mixing is been done by
using shunt circuits so voltage shunt negative
feedback amplifier Okay, now forth you can
also note that it's nothing but current shunt.
Simple now we'll have to learn how I can name
this with different name cleaning configuration.
So we will say that this is done by sampling
and mixing right we will learn different notation
by using mixing and sampling mixing and sampling.
Okay keep this in mind that here we don't
have to use the parameter as voltage and current
we just use this circuit configuration right
as series or Shunt right. So whenever I'm
using mixing and sampling then I have to say
that mixing is if it is mixing it is done
by voltage parameter then obviously that voltage
mixing is a series combination, right? So
voltage mixing is series combination ticket.
So that's why this will be your series will
come first here.It is sampling and mixing
right if I'm using mixing sampling for the
naming then I will use the series. Okay, sampling
is of the type voltage and voltage sampling
is nothing but with the circuit as shunt configuration,
so this is nothing but the configuration as
series shunt configuration. So my another
name is nothing but series shunt configuration,
right? So likewise. I can also form a different
name based on mixing sampling part for further
topologies, right? So for this particular
topologies I can say it is nothing but a series
series Negative feedback amplifier.Okay similarly
over here. I will write this as shunt series
negative feedback amplifier, right? So as
far as this voltage this is shunt mixing and
as far as sampling is done. Mixing is
of the type of shunt and series is it in
the form of voltage with a sampling Okay
here for voltage sampling you're using shunt
circuit.That's why your shunt name will come
into picture for this particular configuration.
And here we will write it as shunt series
because sampling is done with the current
with series circuit. So now another name is  current for this voltage is negative feedback
current series negative feedback voltage series
negative feedback current series negative
feedback as different form with mixing and
sampling configuration. Now here we will have
to learn the separately the analysis of all
the topologies voltage series current series
current shunt voltage shunt and all the topologies