Hello friends here, we will start with the
new chapter all together and the concept is
feedback amplifier. Okay, as for amplifier
is concerned we know that the amplifier is
nothing but if I'm providing small input,
then I'm increasing the strength of the input
at the output side of an amplifier box. Right?
So as far as amplifier box is concerned that
is not black box for me. Okay. So let's understand
the fact that amplifier. This is the box of
amplifier Let It Be whether it is of cscs
multistage amplifier single stage amplifier
three stage amplifier doesn't matters for
me. So this is your input signal that input
signal may be in the form of current
or voltage trigger. So I'm saying that this
is Ii and this is Vi input current or input
voltage here. We will be getting the output
voltage. Our output current right and here
whatever circuit is giving that is nothing
but the gain of an amplifier and that is represented
with the letter A as far as this particular
box is concerned that is not new to me. Right
and now we have to learn that what is feedback
and what how it affects your amplifier operation
and why we need that feedback amplifier. So
let us consider the feedback invention is
done in1928 right so invention of feedback
Is done by Harold Black? And in the year of
1928 that is not important first important
part as far as exam point of view. This is
just you have to remember for extra knowledge,
right and then we will learn what is exactly
feedback and now how it affects the amplifier
operation.Let's start with this fact that
this is let's say feedback amplifier
The Heading of concept of feedback amplifier.
So before learning the feedback, you should
know that whether we have some part of system.
Let's say for example, I'm considering one
particular bag box. Just now. We have studied
that I'm giving the input and I'm getting
the output. That's it. I'm not giving I'm
not utilizing that particular output to give
that particular same signal at the input side
to check that whether output is really the
Part of input or not, right? So that is carried
out by using feedback. So that feedback is
of two types. Okay, so we'll draw that particular
feedback block diagram and then we'll get
to know that how that feedback is important
as far as amplifier is concerned. Here you
have two diagrams in front of you this simple
box that we already have learned that is nothing
but a simple amplifier, right that box is
nothing but simple amplifier where I'm giving
so let's suppose I'm having input voltage
and i am having at the output side output voltage
and this is called as open loop configuration.
This is called as open loop configuration.
Whenever I'm using another block diagram where
this is same amplifier that is forward Amplified.
So in this particular box A is nothing but
the forward gain amplifier and whatever this
box is called as feedback amplifier. This
is called as a feedback circuit and let's
say I'm saying this as input signal let's
say I am saying that it's Vs right Source signal
and this is your output signal. Let's say
Vo, right, whatever output or output voltage
and feeding back to your input side to check
that whether the output is a part of input
signal or not whether there is a distortion
or not. So this is carried out by using the
feedback amplifier. So that is represented
by the letter B. Okay, so they can be output
voltage or output current they can be input
so input current or input voltage, right?
So there are different possibilities can be
carried out by using that we have different
topologies that we have to learn in the next
videos. So let us discuss let us concentrate
on this particular part. This is a closed
loop configuration. This is because whenever
I'm starting with vs and reaching towards
Vo and that Vo is again fed back to the input
side, right so that forms a loop. So that's
why this is called as Loop configuration.
Now important fact is this feedback amplifier
can be here I'm saying this is nothing but
your mixer. This is nothing but mixer where
an adding this Vs.That is Source signal to
your feedback signal or subtracting that source
signal with your feedback signal. So if I'm
subtracting the Vs with VF, this is VF and
saying right if I'm subtracting that VF with
Vs. Then I'm saying that it is called as negative
feedback, right? So that's why Okay, if I'm
saying that this VF is getting added with
Vs. Then I will say that it is nothing but
a positive feedback. So here itself we get
to know that there are two categories of feedback
one is negative feedback and one is positive
feedback. So here in this particular case,
whether it is negative or positive there can
be used in different applications. So whenever
I am using the negative feedback negative
feedback is basically used in amplifier. This
positive feedback is used in basically oscillators
or signal generators. So as far as this feedback
is concerned. So in your laboratory is there
are function generators the where we get the
sinusoidal signal so your triangular signals,
you are Sawtooth wave and M number of ways
we can get from the function generator and
this function generator is an example of positive
feedback, right that will learn the discussed
in detail in the next chapter itself in detail.
So as far as feedback is concerned we learned
that this is positive feedback when I'm getting
when I am adding the source. With your feedback
signal and saying it is negative feedback
If I'm saying Vs is getting subtracted with
VF. Right and whatever signal I'm getting
over here that is called as error signal,
right? So if Vs is not actually equal or equal
to or scaled with Vo then I can say that the
error signal will get generated and depending
on error signal. I will Design my amplifier
such that to get the proper, correct. Output
at the output side. So that is the basic aim
of the feedback amplifiers. Now, we will learn
the mathematical point of view of the negative
feedback and positive feedback as well generalized
form. Let's understand that I'm taking this
example of taking input as voltage and output
as voltage only so it forms an voltage amplifier
where we'll be getting the gain in the form
of ratio of output voltage to the input voltage.
So let us discuss that I know that for open
loop configuration for open lop Configuration
means I'm not providing any feedback. So if
I'm not providing any feedback, what will
be the gain of my complete circuit as an amplifier?
So for open loop configuration this B will
not come into picture then in that case. I
can say that Vi is same as  Vs.
And I can say that Vo divided by Vs is equal
to Vo/ VI
is equal to voltage gain, and that is nothing
but A right so I will say that voltage gain.
I will treat this as with a letter A A is
nothing but Vo upon VI is equal to vo upon
Vs. I will treat that equation number one.
Okay now hold on for closed loop configuration
that means with feedback for closed loop configuration.
For closed loop configuration i am writing
in bracket with feedback. If I'm providing
feedback, then then we'll have to do some
mathematical operation. In this case see to
it that I am learning the negative feedback
in that case. This is the should be negative.
Right this is positive. So whatever VI and
getting that is in the form of VS + VF VS minus VF right. So first equation,
I will be getting in the form of  Vs VF and
VI, right? So I will write it over here the
voltage gain that I will be getting that.
I will treat it as AF voltage gain that I
will treat it as AF and that is equal to
Vo divided by Vs. Let's treat it as equation
number 2. So let's start with the mathematical
operation, right? So from block diagram. as far as block diagram is concerned. I know
that whatever Vo-Vi ratio is nothing but A
whatever Vo-VF ratio is nothing but B so
I can say that A is equal to Vo divided by
Vi. Okay treat it as equation number 3 I know
that B is equal to VF that is nothing but
the output for B and Vo is nothing but the
input for B so VF / Vo is nothing but B.
so we'll treat it as VF / Vo equation number
4 again one mathematical expression will get
from this particular mixer is nothing but
Vs Minus VF is equal to VI. Now what we have
to do we will put the value of VF and Vi
this is because I want to Vs in your voltage
gain formula, right? I don't want VF
and VI, but I can find out. What is VF in the
form of Vo and B. I can find out. What is
the value of Vi in the form of Vo and A again
so that I will get complete. Expression in
the form of Vo and Vs only right? So we'll
treat this as from equation three and four,
we will be getting Vs. I will keep it as it
is - what is Vf Vf is nothing but B into Vo okay simple what is Vi Vi is nothing but
Vo divided by A so here it will be Vo / A
right just do the your mathematical manipulation
here and there left to right right to left
keep Vo at Vo by Vs at the left hand side
and as part of the right hand side, so I will
be getting Vo divided by Vs that is equal
to A  divided by 1 plus AB So as far as this
is this is nothing but you are AF okay. So
this is your last mathematical expression
that we are expecting for your negative feedback
operation for gain perspective. I can conclude
that from this particular operation
from this particular mathematical expression
I can conclude that whatever negative feedback.
I'm providing that will result in the reduction
of gain Okay, so
Here the statement is negative feedback leads
to reduce the gain of an amplifier. So so
far what we have whatever we have discussed
is about the feedback amplifier, but one question
is remained in our mind that why we are using
that negative feedback amplifier by we are
using the feedback if the voltage gain
is reduced right