click the Bell icon to get latest videos
from akira hello friends
now here in the chapter number 5 we are
on the step of the numericals of
negative feedback circuits so before
that we'll have to learn the steps to
follow the numericals
based on feedback amplifiers so we will
follow these steps once we follow these
steps with feedback without feedback to
find out input resistance output
resistance all the stuff related with
their amplifiers and some tricky
problems we'll be discussing in the next
videos so for that we require these
important steps so let's start with the
steps to follow for the numericals of
negative feedback amplifier let's start
with the step number one so first of all
step number one is nothing but the
identification of the feedback topology
so in the circuit circuit can be like
anything for example if your voltage
divider by a C amplifier is given so how
you can identify that whether it is a
first of all whether it is with feedback
or without feedback and then we will
have to understand that if it is with
feedback then what kind of topology that
we have to use right then and only then
we can get that whether the input
impedance is increasing or decreasing
output impedance is decreasing or
increasing so based on the sampling and
mixing part we'll get to know that this
is which feedback topology right so
feedback topology we will have to
understand by just knowing the fact that
the at the output side whether voltage is
sampled or current is sample that means
whether it is shunt circuit or a
series circuit if it is shunt  circuit
then I can say that it's nothing but the
voltage sampling if it is a series
circuit then I can say that it is
nothing but your current circuit so very
simple trick that I'll give you later on
but right now we will learn particular
circuit related to this feedback
amplifiers so if at output
shunt circuit
then I can say that it's nothing but
voltage sampling
I'm specifying focusing more on sampling
and mixing part this is because once you
get which sampling and which mixing we can
easily relate that particular topology
with sampling and mixing part so here I
will say if at the output shunt circuit
then it is a voltage sampling if it is a
series circuit then I can say that it's
nothing but your current
sampling okay
now simply at the output if at input
similarly I will write if it is shunt
circuit then it's a shunt mixing right
if it is series circuit
then it is a
series mixing
okay I will tell you after this
particular video what are the other  numerical info
current for this voltage series voltage
and current series and currents shunt
as well okay so once you identify this
feedback topology we will have to move
further to solve the numerical for
required findings okay one trick that
you have to understand very carefully
take to identify a topology
understand see if
sampling
is
done
at output terminal that means if I'm
saying a complete voltage divider bias
C amplifier is there and from the
output node I have one resistance which
is connected at the input side right so
I can say that that will be your voltage
sampling okay so I can say that it's
nothing but your voltage sampling if
sampling is done at  directly at the
output terminal so hey
so whatever sampling I will be getting
that is nothing but voltage sampling
right so we'll take an example we'll say
this is particular circuit okay
hey if I have taken this sample from
here right this is RF feedback and here
only my output is there right so I can
say that this is nothing but the type of
feedback
we're sampling is
is voltage sampling
so if it is voltage sampling this is
very very simple now to understand the
feedback topology right now in another
case I can say that if I have
this is the voltage and if I'm taking
the feedback from this particular
resistance RF okay so I can say that
this is nothing but sampling is current
sampling it's not a voltage so obviously
it will be current sampling sampling is
of current sampling right so this is the
first method that we have to understand
for the trick okay as a trick and the
second one is about mixing right if
feedback is directly connected to Base
or gate terminal right this is only
related with the this trick is only
related with the FET and BJT amplifiers
so if I'm using the open then that will
not be done for this particular trick
okay so this is for FET and BJT
amplifiers okay
in your syllabus only BJT and FET
amplifiers will be there for negative
feedback so if feedback is directly
connected to the base or gate terminal
then I can say that it will be a shunt
mixing okay otherwise it will be these
series mixing we will take few examples
later on further after this particular
video we will learn the complete
analysis related to each and every
topologies okay so if feedback is
directly connected to the base and gate
terminal FET BJT for FET BJT amplifier
it will be shunt  mixing
otherwise it will be series mixing okay
now we will again take few examples
where we'll get to know that
suppose here I have taken this sample no
matter what sampling is I want to take
the mixing part and
this is the input and I have connected
this complete feedback RF feedback
circuit directly to base so this will be
your shunt mixing ok so this I will name
it as shunt mixing okay in another sense
I can say if
this is your RF okay let's
say this is your output voltage okay
so output voltage is there so this is
your
feedback circuit RF resistance and this
feedback is not directly connected to
the base or gate rather it is connected
with Vs rather I can also say that
mathematically Vs is now equal to this
Vi + this VF okay so it's nothing but
you are series mixing so we have got
some tricks for that particular
amplifiers to identify what is the
feedback topology that is nothing but
your step number one so let's move
towards the step number two that is
nothing but to draw the circuit without
feedback circuit without feedback
Draw circuit without feedback we must
to know which particular feedback
topology I am using okay so for this we
have to draw we have to do some short
circuit we have to do some open circuit
so keep this in mind that I will draw
the general diagram again I don't want
the circuit with feedback okay I want
it without feedback okay
so what should I do
if the circuit is there itself but in fact
should not be avoided then I can say
that I will convert this into your
without feedback circuit and then we
will analyze what is nothing but your
the value of Ri what is nothing but the
value of A what is nothing but the value
of Ro and then later on we will divide it
by your the sensitivity factor that is 1
plus AB very simple now let's see
this is the B okay let's take an example
of voltage series negative feedback in
voltage series for voltage series i am saying
for voltage series output  what will
be your circuit circuit is shunted an
input  your circuit is series so
this is shunt series right so if I am
saying I don't want this feedback right
I have to convert to my this particular
remaining amplifier circuit at the input
side as well as output side so to have
the input side of the amplifier without
feedback then what we'll have to do will
have to short this shunt connection that
means we have to short the output
voltage so its result is short output
voltage this is only for the case of
voltage sampling now to have the output
side right to have the output side what
I will do I don't want this feedback at
the input side right so I want to
eliminate that if it is series
connection then I can say that if I open
that particular circuit between your
series direction of feedback and your
mixer then I can say that it will be
very sufficient to have this circuit
without feedback if I open it right so I
will do the open circuit
at input right this is only example if I
am saying
voltage series right so open it I will
say let's short it connected to the
O/P  okay so if I short it then I will
get at the input side okay so output
change current change the input negative current
input change current output
for all topology we
will write that complete thing in your
topic tabulated form right this complete
thing we will write in a tabulated form
such as let's say that feedback topology
number one number two number three and
number four right I will write in short
that is voltage series voltage shunt for SH
right current series and current shunt
okay first of all you like that which is
sampling and which is mixing okay so
this is what it sampling
this is also voltage sampling
this is current sampling
and this is current sampling moreover
i will write if it is voltage sampling
that I have to write it as shunt
connection
this is shunt connection this is series
connection and this is series connection
okay simple now what we'll have to learn
that what change I have to make at the
input side and what change I have to
make it at the output side so we will
write this as for input for input side
we have to change the output side right
so output we will do whenever it is
shunt I will say that output voltage
short-circuited right here also output
is short-circuited here is a open
circuit at output because it is in
series if I don't want the feedback then
we can say that if I open one of these
series connection if I open that
circuit then I will disconnect the
feedback circuit related to your
amplifier circuit without feedback so
here also I will say it is open circuit
and output right similarly what we will do
at these output side as this is the
series connection I will write this
first as series connection this is the
shunt connection this is the series
connection and this is a shunt
connection then I can say that
this is voltage series this is voltage
shunt
this is current series and this is current shunt
okay very nice so wherever you look as
series we have to open it right so what
change I have to make this is changed
for output side of these without
feedback circuit this is nothing but if
it is series I will say that output you
don't have to change the output rather we are
then we have to change the input side so
open circuit
at input right similarly for the shunt
we have to short circuit at the short
circuit at input similarly as it is a
series I mean write it as open circuit at
input and here it will be short circuit
at input right we will take a few example
a very simple example that we will be
taking as example
this is the circuit
this is the input signal that I am
getting
we will take
okay simple and now we will say that
here it is your feedback
okay this is your RF this is an Re1 this
is our Re2- this is our Rc2 and this is
our Rc1 right no matter what is your DC
voltage here we are considering you are doing
AC analysis right
so with this is feedback circuit
this is given circuit right this is
given circuit with feedback
now we have to draw without feedback
right so we will draw without feedback
circuit without feedback
is okay without Feedback what will they do
first of all we have to identify the
topology as this is your output voltage
that is being given and this is your
input voltage I am saying that output
feedback is taken from the output node
right so it is nothing but your voltage
sampling right here I can say that as
feedback taken from
output node
right it is nothing but your voltage
sampling
simple and now your feedback is taken at
directly at the base so I can say that
here it is your
shunned mixing
okay this is shunt mixing, voltage sampling
so your feedback topology is
voltage shunt with negative feedback so
this topology is voltage shunt
okay now we will you say that for
voltage shunt what we'll have to do for
the input side and output side so for
voltage shunt if you want to develop
this particular input side then what
we'll have to do we'll have to open the
we'll have to do the output as short
circuit right so as this is the voltage
and you say that your output should get
short-circuited if i short circuit this
output this  Rf at the input side will
be down there right so I can say that
at the input side  what we will do this is
your Vs right
yeah
and I can say this is your Rfo
hey this will be your Rf and I can say
that now this is nothing but the change
at the input side so change that input
okay
the rest all the things we have to get
as it is as far as this particular input
side is considered now we will not
change the rest part we will keep this
part as it is this will be our Re only
this is your Rc1 and this is attached to
your
further I want to develop your output
back so that's why I have kept it as it
is. So do the important Rc1 and
this Re1 okay
now what we'll have to do it is the
voltage shunt the negative feedback so
what we'll have to do we all have to do
the same thing that is nothing but
fixed a voltage shunt  negative
feedback so we can say that short
circuit at the input side as well so
what we can do we will do the short
circuit at the input side will consider
this Vs is equal to zero so if we keep
this Vs is equal to zero then I can say
that this Rf will be grounded right so
if this Rf is grounded so I can say this
will be in parallel with your Rc2
as well as AC analysis is considered
okay so this is also and this is also Rf
both  Rf we have to keep in our
circuit right so I can say that this is
nothing but your change at the output so
far whatever we have got it is nothing
but the feedback resistance Rf is placed
at the input side as well as output side
nearly same as that of your Millers
capacitor is Miller's effect okay but we
are not jumping into this Miller effect
but you have to concentrate that
particular theory for developing here
the input side and output side for
without feedbacks of it once we get this
without feedback circuits will move
again for this step number three
fine B find A and find Ri and find
Ro that is nothing but the required
parameter right once we get these this
is nothing but gain without feedback
this A gain without feedback he is a
feedback factor that will be different for
different topology you have to keep this
in mind Ri and Ro once you get that
Ri and Ro we will have to calculate
the value of Rif and  Rof and AF as well
so I will write this here all this and
always Af equal to A divided by 1 plus AB right
so calculate B calculate A once you
calculate both these values we will
easily get the value of Af right then
what we will have to calculate Ri
will be related with Ri multiplied by
1 plus AB or  Ri divided by this is
Rif it's a feedback with feedback
1 plus so this is depends on depending
on type of topology the same case for Ro
will not repeat it again Rof will have
to again calculate with the same way
right so in short once you get the value
of AB Ri and Ro we can easily
calculate all the values of the
parameter required for the negative
feedback amplifier obviously with
feedbacks so we will summarize this
complete video with three steps to solve
the numerical space from the negative
feedback amplifier first step is to
identify the negative feedback topology
based on the sampling and based on
mixing right next step is to draw the
complete circuit without feedback to
develop input side what change we have
to make at the output side to develop at
the output side what change you have to
make at the input side so depending on
that we can develop the circuit without
feedback and the third step is to
calculate all the mathematical
calculation is B,A,Ri Ro and etc depending on
the application depending on the
numerical which comes for you right so
we will stop this particular with this
particular findings we will stop here
next video we will learn few new
numerical which has been used for the Mumbai university