here's another example of feedback we're
gonna look at the ideal amplifier where
the gain is to find us A one ro of
this amplifier is zero and  Rid
differential input resistance is
infinite so because of that we're only
going to look at the AF which is going
to be the feedback gain so identify
first the type we have I-s is my input Io is my output so it's going to be
a shunt series
the next part is to identify the
feedback portion RL is not in the
feedback portion and I-s my input
so here's my feedback part so out of the
feedback portion I want to redraw it and
find R11 R22 and beta I look at the
locations it's connected to the rest of
the circuit here's my input side and
here at this location is my output side
so those are the two locations that I'm
going to modify looking in here I look
at the type I have out which is series
so I leave this side open and find the
equivalent Network which is R2 plus R
in this case on this one I look in this
side for R22 and I have a shunt on the
input side so I short this so R22 is
going to be R in parallel with R2 to
find beta you draw again the same
network you identify what your input
sources and your output so they're both
currents with an input current I put
this as I-f with it going in and I draw
Io at the same location it's
connected to the rest of it here also
going in and beta is defined as I-f over
Io so I need to put these two in
terms of each other here I see that this
is a current in this branch I have a
current and it's going in as a divider
so I can use a current divider to find
this I can say that I-f is equal to a
negative Io branch opposite which
would be R over the summation of both I
can take Io and I get  I-f over Io for beta
again this is beta feed back hoping a
feedback
so now I'm going to redraw the circuit
up here I disconnect the feedback
portion and I replace in the same
location it was before on this side I
replace R22 and at this location I
replace it with R11 going in here was
positive to negative the end and I
replace this with the ideal one which is A
1 times Vn so now I want to find write
these values R2 plus R and this one was
are in parallel with R2 and beta feed
is a minus R over R2 plus R
okay so now I need to get an equation I
want to find from this circuit A which
will be Io over I-s so I need to
get Io Io will be Vin over
the resistances RL plus R in parallel
with R2 and Vin is here so writing
the in in terms of I-s I-s will come in
here
but then this is negative so I have a
negative I-s R2 plus R so I plug
that in and get Io over I-s as A1
negative R2 plus R and I've divided by
the I-s all over  RL plus R in parallel
with R2 so now to find AF
I use this value for A this is my value
for A may rewrite it up here so I small
room
and then it's one plus A again multiplied
by beta feed so the two negatives will
cancel and become a positive so this
cancels was this negative and I get R
over R2 plus R and that is my value for
AF