here we see a feedback circuit so the
first step is to identify the input and
the output it's seen here that the input
is a current source and the output is a
voltage source so this is going to be a
shunt shunt type network after
identifying the type of feedback the
next step is to identify the feedback
portion of the network
here we see from the output to the input
side here's the output side here is an
input side that we have our Rf is our
feedback portion so to find the next
step which is our R11 and R22 and beta
we're going to look at the feedback
portion only to look at R11 we have to
look at this side of the network which
is going to be a shunt so we're going to
ground that side and R11 is going to
be our Rf for R22 again we draw the
feedback portion and we look at this
side of it and then we refer back to the
type and it's a shunt so again we short
shunt and we open a series we leave it
open so this is again going to be our RF
for R22 now for beta we draw the
network again and for beta on the output
side we put the type of output it is in
this case it's Vo so we place Vo on this side it's a current so we
place a short for the current and we
call this I-f  beta is defined as I-f
over Vo
so putting I-f  in terms of Vo
it's going in this direction so it's
negative so we have I-f is equal to a
negative Vo over Rf so to get this
in terms of I-f over Vo we'll
divide here and this ends up being a
minus 1 over Rf as the value for the
feedback so now that we have those three
components we can redraw the small
signal version of this removing the
feedback portion and placing in now this
R11 at the input side R22 at the
output side and then we use the
equations for this beta which is beta
feed back so I'm going to call it beta
feed here and redrawing this with the
small signal circuit
I'm going to short this capacitor which
is large for this is my input side so
I'm going to place our R11 here
the source site is grounded so remember
this is gate source and drain and I'm
going to also include ro and then this
is an ideal current source so that
becomes an open and this is my output
side so I put R22 here and
this is my Vo so from this this is
my new A circuit I want to gather three
pieces of information I want to know the
gain which is going to be Vo over
I -s which will be my A value the
open-loop gain value A I want to know Ri
which will include Rs and I want to know
ro which will include RL in this case
there is no RL so my ro will be at this
location and my Ri will be here and then
the A gain will be from Vo to I-s so
now I want to analyze this circuit so I
need to get Vo in terms of I-s so Vo can be written as a minus the
current minus g-m vgs times these two in
parallel so ro and parallel with R22
which is Rf so I'm going to just put
those values as Rf and here is also Rf
now Vgs is a current source in so I
times R will give me the G and I notice
that Vs is ground so Vgs will be just
VG remember that if it's not you also
have to find the Vs value and get Vgs
which is VG minus Vs so Vgs in this
case then was I-s times Rs and parallel
with Rf
and I can plug that in here and then
divide by I-s to get Vo over I-s
which is my A as A minus g-m ro in
parallel with Rf x Rs in parallel with
Rf so now I have my A value i can also
write Ri and Rf ro so Ri
remember this includes Rs will be Rs
in parallel with Rf and ro which is here
is on the top of the dependent source so
it's gonna be ro in parallel with Rf so
now I have these three values I'm going
to use the feedback equations with the
amount of feedback for Ro and Ri
the amount of feedback whether I divide
or multiply depends on the type of
network I have for shunt type we're
gonna always divide by 1 over or 1 over
the amount of feedback and for series
it's always a multiplication so since
both of these are shunt on both sides
the input side is shunt the output side
is a shunt they're both going to be
divided by the amount of feedback so AF
is going to be A over 1 plus a beta feed
just the feedback value minus 1 over RC
so I get A is a minus g-m ro in parallel
with Rf Rs in parallel with Rf
all over 1 plus again this minus a or a
which is a minus GM ro and parallel
with Rf Rs and parallel
with RF x the beta feedback which is a
minus 1 over RF so these minuses cancel
and give me a positive term so this is
my AF value and this is the feedback
gain that we'll have for this particular
circuit now for Ri Rif this includes Rs
I'm going to divide the Rs in parallel
with Rf which is my Ri value by the
bottom of this which is the amount of
feedback now this includes the RS I do
not want to include the RS for my
overall feedback value so because this
is a shunt type to remove the RS the
term we used was Rin this does not
include RS we have to take this Rif and
it's usually easier to find the value
itself and subtract off the Rs because
it's in shunt that means it's in
parallel so I'm going to have to take
this as a parallel form for Ri or
Rof it's the same thing
it was ro in parallel with RF divided by
the 1 plus a beta feed and so that's
again the same term GM ro in parallel
with Rf Rs in parallel with Rf times
1 over Rf since there's no load RL that
we factored in there this would be also
Rout for this case if we had an RL
included in this
to remove it we again would use one over
rof minus 1 over RL to remove it